Mayank: As I mentioned.
Mayank: Shetty Great.
Mayank: Yeah, sorry, I think now you should be able to see myself as well.
Mayank: So, let me quickly just set things up.
Mayank: Also, I replied to each and every email, to, I think, yesterday or days prior, so hopefully you must have got. If you have replied, I have not seen the same, for sure, so we'll be seeing and replying back.
Mayank: Yeah, cool. So, I hope that all of you took the time and revised the things as well, so that was a very good prerequisite, that you have gone through the
Mayank: Complete revision, because… We were not having any class last weekend.
Mayank: So, let's now begin, everyone.
Mayank: Excuse me.
Mayank: So, I hope all of you are able to see my screen.
Mayank: Each and every one of you are able to see my screen?
Mayank: Great.
Mayank: Cool. Yeah, I hope the voice, audio, and video is all fine, because I'm, as I mentioned, I'm in a new setting.
Mayank: So, if you can help me with that, cool.
Mayank: Yeah, thanks a lot, everyone. Happy DTS day to all of you as well. So, two things, first…
Mayank: Good, we have it here.
Mayank: First, I am at my hometown.
Mayank: Delhi.
Mayank: There was some emergency because of which I was not able to take classes as well last weekend.
Mayank: But yeah, I think, again, a very similar kind of a session, setup is there, so none of you should face any problem.
Mayank: voice.
Mayank: Audio, And screen should be properly visible.
Mayank: I hope the first thing is done right, Abhihan.
Mayank: Great. Second, three days back, I got… some throat.
Mayank: I think, not for an infection or what.
Mayank: Throat infection.
Mayank: Or something.
Mayank: Overall, again, you will be having the class properly today and tomorrow, hopefully. Everything in proper depth.
Mayank: So, not a problem, okay? So, it should not be a problem at all.
Mayank: Just today, I might have a little shorter-down session, like, maybe around 11.30 or 12, because I have some function related to that. So yeah, I think that is just all what you have to do that, okay? Cool?
Mayank: I hope all is good, everyone.
Mayank: Till now, then.
Mayank: Great.
Mayank: Ciao.
Mayank: I'm not enjoying anything, really.
Mayank: TK. Cool.
Mayank: Let's begin.
Mayank: Okay, great.
Mayank: How long will the class go? Normally how we have the class, right?
Mayank: basically… till… 11 o'clock, normal teaching, okay?
Mayank: So, should be fine. And thanks a lot for your wishes and everything, like, really, really happy that so many students messaged me.
Mayank: Thankfully, I'm all good, not a problem at all. There was some other emergency.
Mayank: So, yeah, okay, cool. With that, let's get started, everyone. So…
Mayank: I hope all of you will remember that we were discussing about the MCP, and we are going to do the same thing in depth, okay?
Mayank: Cool.
Mayank: How many of you remember what we were doing, where we were?
Mayank: We were learning about MCP.
Mayank: Right, everyone?
Mayank: Great, then.
Mayank: Cool. Let me help you revise everything as well quickly, so that all of you are on the same page as normally we should be as well.
Mayank: Let me just… Close a few things up.
Mayank: Okay, I think, okay, I'm not using this right.
Mayank: Yeah, this is what we were doing every event.
Mayank: A minute…
Mayank: food.
Mayank: No, you did not miss anything. I am also…
Mayank: Just starting. So, let's start everyone then.
Mayank: Great. So, now, everyone, before we…
Mayank: Now, everyone, before we move forward, let's quickly try to recap on what all we have understood till now.
Mayank: Now, next topic is going to be client, where we are going to understand that what exactly is this client in MCP.
Mayank: Though we have kind of taken an idea through our diagram and everything before.
Mayank: But first, let us quickly try to revise each and everything.
Mayank: Coming to the revision part, we first understood why MCP has to exist.
Mayank: what exactly was the use case because of which we have something known as MCP, Model Context Protocol, and for the same, actually, we have gone in a complete depth
Mayank: To understand that, okay, what was exactly the problem?
Mayank: which MCP solved for us.
Mayank: In the process, not only have we just
Mayank: accepted the solution as it is. We have also seen that why this is one good solution, what exactly and how it got conceptualized, like how we got
Mayank: exposed to ChatGPT, everyone loved it, and then started using it, or we were lazy enough and wanted ChatGPT to do more than just
Mayank: an AI?
Mayank: And of course, then how Anthropic came up with something via which
Mayank: we can connect, or any rather AI tool can connect to the actual outside application which we use. So, be it Google Drive, Slack.
Mayank: GitHub, Gmail, All of these day-to-day applications, how can we directly connect and
Mayank: have them used alongside our AI, so that was the whole aim.
Mayank: And the benefit, why just having or defining tools did not cut it for us?
Mayank: And we were further able to also, of course.
Mayank: See each and everything with the complete
Mayank: practical, right in front of our eyes, using Claude and Claude Desktop, wherever required.
Mayank: So, with respect to that, everyone, now let's move forward and try to learn and master what other things were there.
Mayank: So, if we will see…
Mayank: we understood about the context part, the model part, and of course, the protocol part. Like, those are the three things which makes up our MCP, Model Context Protocol, MCP.
Mayank: As we move forward, we also got to know that how.
Mayank: Our ChatGPT was failing, then it gave us the right answer.
Mayank: how we actually can easily bind the tools as well to our LLM.
Mayank: But, again, what are the benefits and disadvantages of the same? There was a good diagram, I guess, which will help us to quickly revise.
Mayank: Yeah, so…
Mayank: This before and after, very good typograph to help us quickly revise, that what exactly was the case before MCP,
Mayank: And what exactly is the case after MCP? And how MCP made it a lot easier for at least the layman person, because one thing which we will have to understand is that AI is getting used not only by the coders.
Mayank: It is getting used by…
Mayank: Mainly, everyone around us. So, doesn't matter if you are from a tech background or a non-tech background.
Mayank: you are using Cloud or ChatGPT, you are connecting to your day-to-day applications like Google Calendar, Gmail, Slack, everything.
Mayank: With respect to that, I mean, moving forward, we also understood that, okay, what are the major, major positives, and saw the same front, like, in front of us.
Mayank: We, of course, went to the official documentation as well, and tried to create our own MCP server, so that we get an idea about how we effectively have to use the SIM.
Mayank: Anyone is in Outland now?
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: all the notes and everything is properly, added in the GitHub and that, so… Arupesh?
Mayank: I think each and everything is added, okay?
Mayank: So MCP starts… And GitHub, everything is updated.
Mayank: Cool. If you will go on GitHub.
Mayank: Here's my GPT, GitHub.
Mayank: each and everything is properly upgraded. Again, you will see that if you go here.
Mayank: properly all the codes and everything is there. You can go to the class summary as well.
Mayank: So, try to make sure that each and everything is very, very nicely right in front of you.
Mayank: Okay?
Mayank: Good.
Mayank: Shall hello.
Mayank: Now, once the basic idea about MCP was clear, and a little bit idea about what are the different, different parts in it, we jump onto MCP architecture.
Mayank: Now, in MCP architecture, we try to further get down into the main part now, and in the same agreement, you will see that we have majorly three parts, host.
Mayank: Client and server.
Mayank: Now, coming to them, we picked them up one by one. We understood that how we can have a host, and then multiple dedicated clients.
Mayank: And then we understood about host in depth, like, how we have a host like Cloud Desktop, VS Code, Cursor, any chatbot, Codex as well.
Mayank: And then it can connect to the server. Ideally, how the host directly does not connect, but it connects the… to the server via a client.
Mayank: Now This is kind of written, what exactly it is.
Mayank: what it is just now, so let's say, Inspector's own interface.
Mayank: Then real examples, and the one tool that matters, the host never talked to server directly, so we will learn about the same as well now, in the future parts moving forward. Then, similarly, we understood about the server, everyone, that how server is actually where
Mayank: The actions are performed, or basically the application which we want to connect with.
Mayank: In a way, all the applications are having their servers, so we have server for GitHub, for Gmail. We can actually see the same as well, so if I talk and go.
Mayank: to… the clot. In here, when we connect, and say Manage Connectors.
Mayank: we will see that all these are different, different MCP servers only. If I try to add
Mayank: It is asking add custom connector, remote MCP server URL, and the name.
Mayank: So, which means that, yes, all of these connectors in Claude, because we are using Claude and Anthropic as only come up with MCB,
Mayank: We can see right in front of us that how. This is how it happens.
Mayank: So, all these are the different, different servers.
Mayank: And the next part, everyone, so till now, in a way, we have understood about
Mayank: That this exactly is how… We have the architecture. The next topic, which we will now start
Mayank: And the next part is going to be… Blake.
Mayank: our understanding a little bit more in depth about client, so that we can actually make sense and understand. So those all are going to be the thing which we cover in the next part.
Mayank: Any note, anyone?
Mayank: Hey, are we doing a project? MCP server is providing tools or resources to add MCP. Ha, we will be doing that, but first, we will master it in depth, okay?
Mayank: How is host used in production? So, Arun Singh, you will be having
Mayank: an application where you will be using it, which will be connected to AI, right? So, host is that only.
Mayank: In VS Code, when we invoke list of MCP server, there's an option to restart a server. Is that correct? How can a host
Mayank: Restart server, isn't that… should not be allowed. It depends on the type of server current.
Mayank: If it's a STD I.O. server, it can be restarted. So, we will be discussing about the transport layer's type, and that is where it is required, okay?
Mayank: Okay. Is it safe to use publicly available MCP since credentials are associated with different connected? Again, not the safest. It depends from where we are using it.
Mayank: Our web app can also be created as an MCP server, yes, and it can be connected to the host clot, is it right? Yeah, you can.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: the connectors like Mail, Slack, etc. are hosted at server, or they are connected to the application via API. It will depend, again.
Mayank: Normally, it will be… See, API is out of mind, Abhinash. We are not, not discussing around API.
Mayank: Our aim is to make sure that how we can easily get our job done by connecting to an MCP server.
Mayank: After that, if it is connected via API, the normal API is doing it via some other ways, we don't care.
Mayank: So, once I asked my Lord that he send an email.
Mayank: I don't care how MCP is doing that. My concern is how I make a request for MCP to do the same. Clear?
Mayank: Well, sorry.
Mayank: In real-time application, how to install host without clot, desktop, or cursor. Any of your applications at Narayana where you have AI
Mayank: With that.
Mayank: That's a host, okay? How MCP works? Ashutosh, for that, you will have to see the recording of the last… to last weekend class, because I spent a good amount of time in making… in making you understand how it works, okay?
Mayank: Shetty.
Mayank: Cool.
Mayank: The command, Mahesh. This is the command which you're referring to, okay? So…
Mayank: If you will see the recording, everything is there. How to create our own MCP server? We actually have created the same.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: Cool?
Mayank: Sweet.
Mayank: So, let's move forward.
Mayank: So now, everyone, let us continue our conversation and try to understand about the client part in MCP.
Mayank: We already have seen that how we have a host, which is connected to your AI, it connects to the server, and it basically makes sure that now, if you want to do anything.
Mayank: You are able to easily do the same by asking your host. The host goes back to the server with the request and gets your job done.
Mayank: Well, I have always anyway told you that how we have this kind of an architecture, how we are something known as client as well. So, in that way, the way it becomes is that
Mayank: If I just try to copy-paste the same.
Mayank: I will make this horse part a little bit bigger.
Mayank: I will make sure that We are having this server.
Mayank: Now, the main thing to note is that the host, Never directly connect.
Mayank: With your… servers. So, kind of, as I mentioned, I have already Maintain this thing.
Mayank: Each and every of the server gets connected to your host by having a client, so host actually cannot directly talk to your server.
Mayank: Host pops up, something known as Client.
Mayank: So that they can connect with the server.
Mayank: And, few things which you have to note here.
Mayank: host and client.
Mayank: Oh, sorry, server.
Mayank: Speak the same language.
Mayank: Whenever there is a request, so when you, as a human, you ask your host to do something, let's say that you are asking your Claude.
Mayank: That, hey, can you send a request?
Mayank: Can you please send a…
Mayank: email to my manager asking for a leave tomorrow. A very, very basic example, everyone.
Mayank: This is what happens in a very, very high level.
Mayank: So… user, OSP?
Mayank: host.
Mayank: for the…
Mayank: request. So, of course, we will just be asking our host. We are not connecting directly with server or the client. We will be asking the same either to our cloud.
Mayank: Codex, ChatGPT,
Mayank: Claude poured any of the technical or the non-technical ways. I hope this thing is clear, everyone. Yeah, right?
Mayank: This thing is clear, I hope.
Mayank: That user asked the host for the request, right?
Mayank: Client and server speaks the same language, huh? I will make it clear, don't worry. We will, we will learn that language.
Mayank: I heard MCP is not used much in broad. Not totally true, it depends, but it is used, okay?
Mayank: Ciao.
Mayank: So, this thing, user asks, post for the request, you go to ChatGPT or Claude and ask.
Mayank: Whatever you want.
Mayank: Now, what happened, everyone?
Mayank: After this, Actually, your host, your ChatGPT o'clock.
Mayank: they go to the client with that request. So…
Mayank: They will be having the client, and they will make sure that Whatever is a request.
Mayank: They are able to ask the client to complete the same.
Mayank: In a way, for an example, let's say that you ask your ChatGPT or Claude to send an email, the example which I was taking.
Mayank: Your host realized that, hey, I cannot do the same directly. I have no way of sending an email. Just as a very basic example again, your Claude here.
Mayank: It has no direct way of sending an email.
Mayank: it would require that it could connect to the Gmail somehow.
Mayank: that connection, that capability Your Cloud will ask or just change that high-level request to the client.
Mayank: the client will then make sure that it connects further with server. So this is exactly how it happens, step by step.
Mayank: Client, everyone then sends a structured request.
Mayank: So, it sends a structured request.
Mayank: to the server.
Mayank: Once, The server gets the request.
Mayank: And this is where the same language thing comes into picture. The server understands a particular language. Now, that language is something known as JSON RPC, okay? So, we will talk about what exactly this JSON RPC is.
Mayank: The client sends back the response.
Mayank: in a structured request only. So, again, you are asking your
Mayank: host, which is your ChatGPT or clock.
Mayank: Okay, so they have already popped up a client which connects to your server, which is your MCP servers.
Mayank: Your request, whatever it is.
Mayank: So, again, it can be a very simple request, like send an email, or make an event in my calendar.
Mayank: It reaches client, client changes that into a language which server can understand, server sends back the response, and then client further makes sure everyone
Mayank: That it is able to Tell your host that, hey, this is what happens, again, in an understandable manner.
Mayank: So, kind of, this is how your complete communication happens.
Mayank: You ask directly the host, Host forwards the same to client.
Mayank: They both are able to communicate with each other because they speak the same language. Now, there are multiple ways through which they can connect
Mayank: Through which they can stay connected, through which they can check if they're alive, etc.
Mayank: And, of course, multiple things which your server can do, so… which we will discuss in the next part.
Mayank: Funz?
Mayank: The server sends back the response to the client. The client understands the same.
Mayank: And send it back to the host in a much better way.
Mayank: In which hosts can understand.
Mayank: The main point, host, And this should be client, my bad.
Mayank: client and server speaks the same language. So, again.
Mayank: host cannot directly connect with your server. So, client and server, they will be speaking the same language, and that language, everyone, is known as your JSON RPC. So, if I show you the same in the main
Mayank: Documentation. So this, everyone, is the official, official documentation.
Mayank: And if we see in the architecture side.
Mayank: We will actually notice that how?
Mayank: We are having.
Mayank: MCP host, MCP client, and MCP server, and in a very similar manner, how we are connecting, or client gets connected to the server. So, see? The AI application that coordinates and manage one or multiple MCP client, a very good example, Claude.
Mayank: a component that maintains a connection to an MCP server and obtains connections from an MCP server and for the MCP host to use.
Mayank: a program that provides context to MCP clients. So, again, just to make it a little bit more clear to understand.
Mayank: This, everyone, what you see right in front of you is actually your host, so whatever we are seeing.
Mayank: In this complete red.
Mayank: That all is our host, which is your cloud.
Mayank: Inside Claude, we are aware that right now, as well, I'm connected to all these different, different MCP servers. So, these are your MCP servers.
Mayank: But this host, it has not connected directly to your server.
Mayank: for each of the MCP servers, let's say if there is a Gmail server, everyone.
Mayank: It has, in the backend, started off a MCP client.
Mayank: That client actually connects to your server.
Mayank: So, if there would be anything, if there would be any request which you ask in here.
Mayank: it will be sent to the MCP Client.
Mayank: This is your MCP.
Mayank: So what?
Mayank: And this will be your MCP host.
Mayank: So this is how it happens. Now, since it is started in the backend, we can create our own server, sorry, client as well, which we will see again. But since this is started in the backend, as of now, I cannot show you it directly that, hey, this is where the client is there.
Mayank: They connect with each other. Now, any requests which you send.
Mayank: It will be forwarded to the client.
Mayank: Then your client will make sure everyone that it sends to the server, server will send back the response, and finally.
Mayank: the response goes back to the host, Innovate can understand, and then we can just easily get the work done via the MCP server.
Mayank: I hope this is fine, everyone. So, each connector's the client would be different, right?
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: And one more very important thing to note.
Mayank: Each and every server gets a separate client, so what do I mean by that?
Mayank: This odd there is a… One is to one relationship.
Mayank: Petween.
Mayank: The client and the server.
Mayank: So, for each of the Server, you have a separate client.
Mayank: And again, very, very important to understand, host.
Mayank: cannot directly connect with the server. They don't understand each other. So, host, kind of has a friend service.
Mayank: Which is client, which it pops up.
Mayank: If you have multiple servers, you will be needing multiple clients. So, the same host every event.
Mayank: It can actually have Or rather, will have.
Mayank: multiple clients.
Mayank: So that it can… Connect.
Mayank: with multiple MCP.
Mayank: SOMIS.
Mayank: So… So, a simple one-on-one relationship.
Mayank: And there are multiple benefits of this one-on-one relationship as well, everyone. Let me go and ask directly on the clock.
Mayank: Oh, sorry, on the official MCP, what is the benefit?
Mayank: off.
Mayank: 1 is 2-1.
Mayank: MCP?
Mayank: Client.
Mayank: And server.
Mayank: connection.
Mayank: Meanwhile, it answers, I think, easily we can even come up with the…
Mayank: positives of this thing, because it is a little bit easier to understand. So, the very first one, everyone is off
Mayank: Your scalability.
Mayank: Rather than one client having to connect with multiple servers, it is… of course, a lot more scalable.
Mayank: Second, everyone, is around the parallelism.
Mayank: Since now we are having multiple clients.
Mayank: If we want to have a request where we are connecting with multiple
Mayank: servers, let's say the Gmail and the calendar server, it can happen in parallel. If I ask my Claude that, hey, can you please check my calendar
Mayank: And Palli also send an email to my manager for this and that. Just as an example, it can make sure that it can do the same.
Mayank: By making it a single call.
Mayank: It is very, very good with respect to the security.
Mayank: If in case there is a problem with one of the clients, or one of the connections gets compromised.
Mayank: Other thing will not be having any issues, because they are decoupled with each other.
Mayank: So, in this ways, we are having decoupling, that is, one connection is not have to do anything with the other connection, and that makes that, in the security part, each and every one of these connections can have different authorization handles as well.
Mayank: So that is why it is very, very important, everyone.
Mayank: And I think…
Mayank: it is… okay, I hope it will give the answer. Normally, it tries to give you the answer. But yes, normally, it has just explained us in a similar fashion, but, yeah. Overall, there are… these are the major
Mayank: Overall benefits, everyone, which we should be aware about.
Mayank: That is regarding our complete.
Mayank: MCP.
Mayank: Host, client, and server, the three main important parts.
Mayank: which are present in our MCP architecture.
Mayank: Plugins are different. Current plugins are connectors plus skill, but yes, they are… having MCP in them.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: If user asks to give input, fetch me hacker news and also send email to this, this, and what is this? So it will assign different clients for each work.
Mayank: It is not like that, kapil. It will try to first check if it can do the work.
Mayank: Second, if it needs to connect with MCP servers, it will try to connect With the… same.
Mayank: And it can connect with different, different MCP servers if required. So if you are asking for fetching the latest hacker news, news.
Mayank: and it is having a MCP server for that, it can easily connect with that.
Mayank: Similarly, for sending an email, it will connect and have another thing, and in that way, it is there, so you can have multiple of these clients, okay?
Mayank: How many maximum clients we can have? I don't think there is some limit as such.
Mayank: These are not very heavy connections, if you think about, and we will see in transport layer that how
Mayank: Majorly in the local side as well, it is not the issue, okay? If multiple users ask same question, then do it connect single or multiple?
Mayank: Again.
Mayank: If all of us are asking different, different questions to Claude, my Claude is having multiple of clients, which are for me, okay?
Mayank: A client some process thread, yes. It is kind of a process which your host starts.
Mayank: Cool.
Mayank: So, Rashim, that is the idea. Now, host can be huge in number. Then, per connection by MCP client server needs highly scalable server. So, we are able to scale up that up. Okay?
Mayank: Coming to the security endpoint, it may happen that Gmail get authorized via OAuth.
Mayank: then your GitHub gets authorized via some key, etc, so they can have different, different kind of authorization mechanism as well.
Mayank: Claude may have multiple clients to single server.
Mayank: Normally, we have one is to one. We have one client for one server, not that bits.
Mayank: Does it have any performance issue if you use 100 plus MCPs? Host will not.
Mayank: On the complete server where it is running, that can have a little bit of effect, okay?
Mayank: If I load multiple MCP servers into an AI application, will they automatically consume the context window? It, again, depends on how you have defined your
Mayank: Application. It will all depend on that matter.
Mayank: If you have said that, okay, every time I need to send that information, then it will do that.
Mayank: If many users are using the same client, how will it process? So, Sachin, that is what I'm saying.
Mayank: Each user has its own host, right? If I am using my cloud.
Mayank: My cloud is having the clients. It is not that…
Mayank: you are using my Cloud or Claude as this decoupled. No.
Mayank: Each user has its own host.
Mayank: That own host is having its own client, so just understand it like that.
Mayank: Thank you.
Mayank: How to identify which client is for which server? You don't have to identify that.
Mayank: If you are creating, then yes, but it's pretty simple. Each client, when it starts off, you tell that, hey, this is the server I want you to connect with, okay?
Mayank: Is there any fallback for MCP Server in case of failure? Yes, we should be knowing about the failures, and we should be then handling the same, provided we are creating MCP Server for complete scratch.
Mayank: Yes, kapil. Host is that only, which takes input.
Mayank: What if I have built an AI application that is consumed by multiple users? Makes sense? Would that not create overdone MCP servers? How do we handle that? So, the server thing is normally how you create and handle a server. If your server is having a lot of
Mayank: let's say, traffic and everything. We just try to make sure that we are having the load balancing
Mayank: containerization. We are having multiple instances of the server, so that is the case.
Mayank: If one client is done, how can another client will be… will handle and forward the corresponding server? How?
Mayank: What do you mean by client is done?
Mayank: Host is connected, right? So host will take care of this connection. If this is done with the part, it will get back the response. Then it can call the other client with that knowledge.
Mayank: Host is having the brain, right?
Mayank: If I give multiple requests to the same client, how will it process on the same host? Again, you don't handle that. You give your request to the host. If you give it multiply to the client.
Mayank: It will, again, depend on how your client, or how your host is creating this client, if it will be taking it in a queue manner, that is one after the another, or in a parallel manner, okay?
Mayank: Okay. Do I need multiple NCP clients for different MCP server every time? Yes, because it's a one-on-one connection, okay?
Mayank: For example, I'm sending same request for 10 clients, so all will be connected to same server.
Mayank: Yes, now you can have a batching request as well.
Mayank: You can have a request which is batched, where you are sending the request, and having multi… in a single request, you are having 10 actions, example, okay?
Mayank: Multiple client connecting same server. No, 1 is to one. It's not NS21, not 1S2N. 1 is 2-1. As simple. Okay?
Mayank: Cool?
Mayank: Excuse me.
Mayank: How my host knows which client to connect.
Mayank: it has that information. Now, when you are having your host created, it knows that, okay, the client, which application it is connecting and everything. So, host is having that idea.
Mayank: And again, I will explain that. We will see that how it connects and understand that, okay, this host, it is having the tools related to the clients, sorry, to the Gmail server, etc. Okay?
Mayank: Server is not in our machine, right? If we are using an external MCPI, it runs on their machine.
Mayank: Can there be a case when more than two different users use the same IP or client to connect to its server?
Mayank: Again, see, there's a Gmail MCP server, we are…
Mayank: People are connecting, but at my end.
Mayank: I will just have a single
Mayank: One minute, yeah. At my end, my Cloud, my host, will have a single server, a single client to connect to the Gmail server, that's something.
Mayank: Chica?
Mayank: better to use async with MCP server, but again, MCP is not a single function call. Everyone, I hope you do understand MCP is a complete protocol, right?
Mayank: So that is why it is happening.
Mayank: If two servers has the same capability, context understanding is done by host, then decide which client needs to be called. So that is where we have that approach. Again, let me showcase that, how it happens, it will be much clearer.
Mayank: What if you request for Gmail and GitHub? Will it be single client? No, it'll be two clients.
Mayank: How it will be single client.
Mayank: If one client is down, how other client will handle the request and forward to the respective server?
Mayank: Okay, cool.
Mayank: Hkd, I hope everyone, you do understand that you…
Mayank: are having one is to one connection. If a client is down, we can have the same created up. What do you mean by how it will connect to the other client, etc? Host is able to connect to all these clients, right?
Mayank: Please continue your teaching, it is very slow. Solving doubts is very, very important, so no worries, okay?
Mayank: Cool, everyone.
Mayank: Challow. Let's move forward.
Mayank: Great.
Mayank: If the server is down, then everything is down, like, you cannot do anything if server is down, okay?
Mayank: shallow.
Mayank: I'm not sure that why people have still not revised the class. Please revise the class. All these things are kind of explained.
Mayank: Piga?
Mayank: Let's move forward.
Mayank: There are a few doubts, I will take many of them in towards the end, so don't worry, okay?
Mayank: So, great everyone, now let's move forward and continue our discussion, and next, now cover this one very important topic, which is known as your MCP primitive.
Mayank: Now, MCP primitive is a pretty simple thing. It is actually all the Different, different things.
Mayank: which your server can offer. So, in the last part, we understood about an MCP server, and we already have seen that how.
Mayank: we are having servers for different, different things, like, this actually is also an MCP server only.
Mayank: We kind of have understood the same by a clot part.
Mayank: Now…
Mayank: all what your server can offer, that is known as MCP primitives. There are 3 major things, everyone, which your MCP primitive can offer, and that is right in front of us.
Mayank: the tools, the resources, and the prompts. So let's take them one by one and understand the same.
Mayank: Tools are something which we will be using the most, or normally which gets used the most.
Mayank: And it is actually an action.
Mayank: Which… AI can ask the server, to perform.
Mayank: So, a very simple example, everyone, sending an email. If you want to make sure that you are going to send an email to Gmail, well, that's a tool call, in a way. That is something which MCP will do by calling the tool. So, that is what your tool,
Mayank: Primitive is everyone?
Mayank: Second is something known as resources. So, if you will see right in front of you, second is something known as resources. And all these definitions, again, if you go on server, it is kind of mentioned here.
Mayank: But still, let me explain you in a way I want to.
Mayank: It is your data sources.
Mayank: that AI can read.
Mayank: Normally, they are static in nature, something which doesn't change. A very good example of this, everyone.
Mayank: When you have a GitHub repo.
Mayank: In your GitHub repo, you can have README, right?
Mayank: Which normally doesn't change.
Mayank: And if required, your host, example your Cloud, can read that thing directly via the MCP,
Mayank: And again, when we make a connection, when the host starts off, and it starts a client to connect to your MCP server.
Mayank: it is able to understand what all your MCP server is offering, and we will discuss that, how it does that as well, just in a bit.
Mayank: But it is aware that, okay, these are all the resources.
Mayank: Which my server is having.
Mayank: First tool, second server, which is data sources that AI can read, they are static in nature.
Mayank: A very good example, everyone, as I mentioned, is your, let's say, Readme.
Mayank: Files.
Mayank: Or, if, let's say, there is a…
Mayank: MCB server of a database, DP like SQL, etc, then it will be your schema.
Mayank: Okay? So any file or any resource which you feel that will not be changing, it is static, which might be required by your
Mayank: Overall, AI, or host, that is what goes in resources, everyone.
Mayank: And next, or the last one, everyone, are predefined prompts, okay? So, prompts.
Mayank: Coming to prompts, we have… pre-defined.
Mayank: Prompt template.
Mayank: Which… help AI to do Work.
Mayank: better.
Mayank: So, just to explain a little bit more on all these things, because last one is… this prompt thing is a little bit tricky, but yeah, with an example, it can easily be understood.
Mayank: Let's say that, and I think I can go in here and explain you the same, so just let me close it.
Mayank: Prompts provide reusable template. They allow MCP server orders to provide parameterized prompts for a domain or showcase on how to best use the server.
Mayank: Now, again, let's try to understand this with an example. Let's say that you are asking your
Mayank: Chad repeat, you are asking your Claude to send an email to your manager, okay? So, very simple. You are asking, send an email
Mayank: to your… Manager. Okay, so very simple.
Mayank: This request, because it is very simple, your AI can just use the send email tool.
Mayank: And just send a very basic kind of an email. So it can just be a very, very basic kind of an email, which is going to have a subject, everyone.
Mayank: So, it is having subject.
Mayank: And, of course, it will be in a similar fashion.
Mayank: having the book.
Mayank: But now what happens, everyone, now what exactly can happen is that this might not be a very right way of sending an email in a company setting, or the way your company follows it, or even, let's say.
Mayank: The way you will be taking it up.
Mayank: In a real life, like, normally it's fine that, yes, it will just send an email, But…
Mayank: we might require more things in our email. In a very good… again, a very good example.
Mayank: Let's say that you are asking your AI to create a GitHub issue.
Mayank: So, for people who are not aware, let's say if I go on GitHub. MCP.
Mayank: Just, let's say, GitHub official MCP servers.
Mayank: there are issues created in GitHub. Now, of course, once you connect GitHub MCP to Claude, it can create issue for you.
Mayank: But then it can very well happen that the issue which will be created
Mayank: That will not be very much detailed, it might not have all the information, because your cloud, it can just create it simply, right? It can just have a very simple way of creating an issue, not providing all these things, any file, etc.
Mayank: This is where, everyone, prompts are able to help your AI work better.
Mayank: They give all the information.
Mayank: And gives you that, okay, for doing this particular kind of an action, what are the best instructions?
Mayank: Once your AI understands those best instructions, and this is very much akin to how we are having
Mayank: skills in our modern-day AI, how we can use a skill, everyone, and that skill will be further able to easily
Mayank: just get our work done in a much better manner. So that is how it happens in a modern, AIs now, okay? And of course, it will be able to then do the work a lot better. So…
Mayank: Just as a very good example, pay attention.
Mayank: Examples team and workflow. Prompt provides structured templates for common tasks. In the travel planning, like, let's say, for example, in the travel planning, where everyone named
Mayank: title, description, it is giving you the complete idea about the argument as well. So, completely, it is telling you that, hey.
Mayank: If you are planning a vacation, Okay?
Mayank: If there is a request of planning a vacation.
Mayank: Maybe you can just ask about and get me these things. The destination, Duration, budget, interest.
Mayank: So, now everyone, rather than an unstructured natural language input, the prompt system enables selection of the plan navigation template, so this template can kind of get picked up.
Mayank: Structured input.
Mayank: your AI will kind of know that, hey, these are the things which I need to provide.
Mayank: And across the workflows, across multiple calls, it will be very consistent now. Because, as an example.
Mayank: If someone connects to an MCP, that MCP is having planned vacation prompt.
Mayank: It will always be asking for these four things, and that is how your AI will now be performing a lot better. So rather than it just giving you destination, sometimes it is giving you the budget, sometimes it is just giving you the duration or the destination, it can have a request created on this manner.
Mayank: So, in a way, we have made sure
Mayank: that our complete request is getting done a lot better. So, predefined prompt template, which help AI to work better. So, this is exactly what prompt helped us to do in our complete MCP run.
Mayank: Before call, how AIF hosts know about this prompt, next part, Vinaj. Just the next, very next part. All the function in primitive, okay?
Mayank: Sunny.
Mayank: Oop.
Mayank: Yeah, so, let us continue, then I will take the doubts, everyone.
Mayank: So, to quickly help you understand and revise, everyone, this is actually, let's say, the tool. So, GitHub create issue. The AI decides not you, like, which tool exactly to call. It can, of course, ask you. So, tool create issue.
Mayank: it will be able to actually do an action right in front of… in our application. So, similarly, send email and everything. It is kind of what can be directly used. Next, everyone, is your resources. So, coming to resources.
Mayank: It can actually… or you can have some resources kept, everyone, which can be referred to. A very good example of this is actually the database one. So you can have this schema file, which your AI can read through, so that it can work in a much better manner, okay?
Mayank: And last, everyone, is something which is known as prompt, as I mentioned. So, coming to the prompt.
Mayank: prompt, before and after template. So, again.
Mayank: It can be a lot structured if you are having this particular prompt.
Mayank: kind of kept, so your prompt can make sure that it is giving your AI the information that, hey, this is how this task can be done a lot better.
Mayank: Now, next, everyone comes.
Mayank: functions, of the primitive.
Mayank: Now, when it comes to the functions of the primitivore, I would like to rather call it primitive functions only.
Mayank: So, coming to primitive functions, everyone, this is actually what allows your AI to understand what all your server supports.
Mayank: So, as of now, in a very simple sense, we are still having host?
Mayank: And this host, we kind of know that it starts off with a Client.
Mayank: And this client, everyone, finally connects to my server.
Mayank: Now, what happened, everyone, is that when this connection happens, when your client connects to the server.
Mayank: During the initial part, and we will see the same in the MCP lifecycle, and what are the different, different steps.
Mayank: But, initially only, it can ask your server for all these primitives. So, we have 3 types of primitives, everyone.
Mayank: Let's take them one by one, like the functions.
Mayank: Coming to the tools.
Mayank: There are two functions.
Mayank: your client, it asks first that, hey, if you can list all the tools. So, there is a list, everyone.
Mayank: And there is a call. These are the two functions.
Mayank: The very first time your host connects… sorry, your client or host connect to the server.
Mayank: it asks your server to list all the tools it is having. So again, if you go back to tools.
Mayank: You will notice that how there are two methods.
Mayank: Tool list and tool call.
Mayank: So, a very good example.
Mayank: Just… as and when you're… Claude.
Mayank: We'll, let's say, connect to Slack here.
Mayank: it will send a request to Slack and ask it to list all the tools it is having, so that your Cloud is aware that, okay, what exactly?
Mayank: my server can do. As a very basic example, right in front of you, from the official documentation.
Mayank: This is how it will be receiving the request. So, once it sends
Mayank: Initially on the connection, tool slash list.
Mayank: This is how you can get the response, everyone. The name of the tool, the description, what exactly is the schema, what are the required ones, the properties.
Mayank: Origin, destination, date, and this is the required thing.
Mayank: Once your AI knows that, hey, these are the tools which my server has.
Mayank: And of course, description and everything will have a very, very big role to play. And if you remember, actually, when we created our tools.
Mayank: In the server, we also gave this description and everything.
Mayank: Your AI will be able to take a much better call.
Mayank: On exactly which particular action your server can perform, and it can then ask.
Mayank: the server to do that particular action by using this call method. So again, understand the same very, very quick, properly.
Mayank: When the connection gets created, everyone, that is when you will be adding a server here.
Mayank: It will list all the tools.
Mayank: When it will be calling the tool.
Mayank: It will make sure. So, as you can see right in front of you.
Mayank: Tools enable AI application to perform action on behalf of users. In a travel planning scenario, the AI application might use several tools
Mayank: To help book a vacation.
Mayank: Searchlight's origin, destination, date. So, it is able to send this exact origin, destination, and date, because initially it got the idea that, hey, this is how my tool works.
Mayank: So, first, it got the information via to slash list.
Mayank: Next, it is able to call that particular tool via tool clause, tools… Slash coin.
Mayank: So I hope this thing is clear, everyone.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: How client knows if server added or deleted any tools? There is a…
Mayank: subscription kind of a thing there, Satanarayan.
Mayank: And it kind of regularly checks if something has happened or not, okay?
Mayank: I heard MCB is now stateless, some new features are added. Ashish, that has been done towards the August end. First, we will understand the previous architecture, then I will cover that what all has changed, okay?
Mayank: Where does AI or host store these details?
Mayank: it is stored in the MCP logs and everywhere, and then it is sent in every call, etc, okay?
Mayank: Cool, everyone?
Mayank: Let's move forward.
Mayank: Let's move forward, so we can agree it.
Mayank: In a similar fashion, everyone, like, we have four tools. We, of course, are having the primitive functions for resources as well.
Mayank: So, the very basic one are, of course, to list, as we can see in here as well, to list and read a resource. Again, it is not anything which
Mayank: will do an action for you. It is just your, static resource, right? So, as you can see in here, resource slash list, list available direct resources.
Mayank: Resource template list. Discover resource templates, array of resource template definitions. I think this has been decently added.
Mayank: Resource lead. Retrieve the resource contents.
Mayank: Again, if there is a schema file, it can just retrieve the same.
Mayank: And now there is Subscription Listen as well, which can monitor the changes in your resource. So if… normally we have the static one only, but yes, if and when they get changed.
Mayank: This is how it will get to know that, hey, something has changed in here. A very basic example, continuing with the travel planning example, resources provide AI applications with access to relevant information.
Mayank: Calendar data, events 2024, so it can have all the holidays or events which are in the 2024 year.
Mayank: Travel documents, passport PDF, of course, which will be static in nature, it will not change. Maybe the guidelines on the country which you are going, the visa process.
Mayank: and previous itineraries or something, which we can save as well. So once your AI gets the context, it will easily be able to get a much better overall approach. And yeah, now, easily, you are having the URI template.
Mayank: Name, title, description, and what is the type?
Mayank: So, MIME type is application slash JSON, PDF, markdown, all these things can be saved in here. And yeah, it can be a proper file as well, everyone. So, easily, you can have a complete file.
Mayank: via which your AI can get this particular thing.
Mayank: And last, for the prompt as well, we have the list and the get, so when we talk about
Mayank: Prompts as well, everyone.
Mayank: There is list and kit.
Mayank: In here, we have list, get.
Mayank: And what was the other one?
Mayank: Template list and listen.
Mayank: So… Template, list, and listen.
Mayank: So, yeah, these are all the functions, everyone, as you see right in front of you. This is actually what your… what makes your MCP servers usable. So, initially, when
Mayank: your MCP server starts.
Mayank: sorry, MCP client start, it tries to hit and get the tools, the resources, and the prompts which are available, so that in future, based on that knowledge, it can access the relevant
Mayank: Whatever it wants, be it tool, be it resource, or be it prompt.
Mayank: And that is how, effectively, our complete
Mayank: With the help of this primitive everyone, we are able to make sure that we are able to.
Mayank: do each and everything as required on our MCP server, because now we are aware about its capability.
Mayank: So, if you will see, we know what it offers. We got all these things. We have a specific function between the same.
Mayank: And then we can just use it as it is, as it is intended to be.
Mayank: What is the main benefit of resource if you have tools? Tune can also call any resource. No. Again, Amit, can you have a README file in a tool?
Mayank: What is the difference between list and get?
Mayank: Then in the list will, resource, let's take it with respect to the resource. List will tell you what all resource it is having, that, hey, I'm having D2B file, I'm having schema.
Mayank: GET will get that exact file for you. Clear?
Mayank: List and get.
Mayank: Oh, no.
Mayank: Does a server call the tool rather than the agent?
Mayank: Does the server call the tool rather than the agent?
Mayank: Right, it's the wrong question. Palli Bhar host will call it, right?
Mayank: host, Tell the client a client calls the tool.
Mayank: Why do we need template and resource, and what listen will do?
Mayank: Listen will tell you if there has been any changes, so kind of update, okay?
Mayank: Templates, discover resource template, and array of resource, template definition, unless it has been added recently, so we can check it. But as the name suggests, it will just give you a template for a particular resource, so that maybe if you want to create more templates, or sorry, more particular resource, it can help you in that. So as a very basic example.
Mayank: If I want to create and store any other schema, that is where it will be done, okay?
Mayank: Why prompts are required? Tools and resources should be sufficient for any client to get the necessary information for server and execute. No? Exactly, no.
Mayank: Right? Example is right in front of you.
Mayank: Prompt is effectively telling you that what is the right way of doing it.
Mayank: A much better way of doing the same.
Mayank: An email tool will just have the instructions for sending an email.
Mayank: But, as a very basic example, prompts can have
Mayank: Ask for leave kind of a prompt. Then, professional communication prompt.
Mayank: then we can even have, maybe some request kind of a prompt, so it will help you to do it much better. So, whereas sending an email is a tool.
Mayank: Sending an email for a… to the manager, to your subordinates, to your client, they can be having different ways. That is where Raut will help you, right?
Mayank: We have tool description, why we need, again, the README file-like resource. Again, I'm not sure why all these questions are coming.
Mayank: I hope you know that README file is a separate thing, right? How does that compare to a tool
Mayank: description, Bhu?
Mayank: If there is a GitHub repo.
Mayank: README is a different file, right?
Mayank: Tool description is different.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: Extremely sorry, everyone. I hope it is not very high on your ears, but yeah.
Mayank: Can we use tools to refresh the resources dynamically if there are any changes in the schema? Huh? We can have. It is separate, like, tool has nothing to do with that, okay?
Mayank: As part of developing a client, do we need to call each of the primitives on a need basis? Yeah, they are called initially, yes.
Mayank: Okay. If I missed any doubt, everyone, quickly ask that out, so that, before we move on to the next one, how to invoke MCP client, since we always can't mention the right keywords. Your host take care of the same. If we are defining it, which we will do in future, we will see that how can we invoke it.
Mayank: So, the prompts we get to the server, we use it while calling the tool.
Mayank: Yeah, I agree, yes.
Mayank: Okay? Single or multiple prompts mapped to individual tools, or single prompt for all MCP tool offering. No, no, there can be multiple prompts for multiple tools, or for a single tool. Okay?
Mayank: So, like that, how many templates there would be? Like, it's NS, no? Ha, AHA, but again, we will not be creating infinite number of templates or anything.
Mayank: We will be having, like, for example, in a Gmail server, there will be maybe 15-20 types of Gmail.
Mayank: If I have two Gmails, can we create multiple clients for the same Gmail connector? No, it's a one-on-one connection.
Mayank: You should then have two servers.
Mayank: Does it cache the tools? Now, in the latest version, it does.
Mayank: So, yes, it is kind of caching.
Mayank: For everything we ask, there would be a template for it with the server. No, why?
Mayank: How will that be the case, Priya?
Mayank: When we talk about batch equipment, is it only one client handling 10 requests? Let's say, send 10 emails to 10 users? It will depend on how the server has been handled. If your server is having a tool which can have that 10 requests sent, else it will be one by one.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: What is skills?
Mayank: Just search about it, see skills in Cloud, and you will get to know that. There are predefined instructions.
Mayank: Can we maintain the version of prompt in the MCP server? Yes, MCP primitive resource and prompts are mandatory. No, they are not mandatory.
Mayank: How do we define the authentication? There are different, different ways, we will discuss about that. We kind of covered that in the last one as well.
Mayank: What are components in FCP servers?
Mayank: Where are the component?
Mayank: We will see it.
Mayank: Grm, again, please don't spam. I think I'm totally taking your questions. Can you please explain resources? Can you tell me, JRM, what you did not understand in the resources?
Mayank: I told you, you know, static information which is required.
Mayank: So if you have a schema… okay, everyone, give me an idea. Where will you keep schema?
Mayank: If you have a Deb connection, where will you keep schema?
Mayank: Is that a V?
Mayank: Resource is always static, it is near static. It is not something which will get updated frequently. It can get updated, but not frequently.
Mayank: Okay? Okay, just tell me one thing, everyone. You are having MakeMyTrip MCP.
Mayank: If…
Mayank: let's say people normally ask a lot of questions around, let's say, going to Dubai. And Dubai has a visa thing.
Mayank: visa process.
Mayank: There is a visa document. Where will you be like to save it?
Mayank: Don't you think that you can save it easily in a resource part, everyone?
Mayank: In the resource section.
Mayank: Resources.
Mayank: Same for your passport, etc, if you are getting it.
Mayank: For emails, you can maybe have…
Mayank: Any of the company documents which you use a lot.
Mayank: Okay?
Mayank: can be stored in Deb? You can, but again, from the MCB point of view, resource is a much better option.
Mayank: Clear? So I've given you multiple examples. For GitHub, it can be a README. For a Deb, it can be a schema file.
Mayank: For a travel example, which we saw on the MCP official website, it can be passport, it can be visa documents, visa checklist, etc.
Mayank: But you said schema is a resource, so I'm still saying schema is a resource. Schema CAN be a resource, I'm not saying it is a resource. How different resource of MCP with RAG? Totally different, okay?
Mayank: Yes, we do define, if we create MCB, how to authenticate. It can or cannot be there. It depends on what kind of server we are creating.
Mayank: Is resource solving the purpose we are using RAG? No. It's a different thing, okay?
Mayank: How to fetch resource, accurate user requests from the resource, like Avi next part here.
Mayank: Do resource and prompts have impact? Like, tools have an LLM context? They have an effect, that's why they are there, okay? Will there be any mapping between tool list and prompt list? Not mapping as such, like, they just normally tell us that, hey, if you're trying to do this thing, this is the right or the best approach for doing it.
Mayank: For example, here, it tells you
Mayank: That, for plan a vacation, these are the best arguments which you should have ready. Once you have this ready, then server can make a much better call. It is not that, hey, if you need to plan a vacation, this is the tool you should call. No, no, no, not like that. It is not some mapping or like that, kHI. This tool could best use Kante, it is not that.
Mayank: It is for an action, normally.
Mayank: Cool. Do resource and prompts have impact like tools have an LLM context? Yes, it will have that, okay?
Mayank: Where are the logs stored to analyze or debug it when it fails? Show you for GitHub connector.
Mayank: One thing, if we create MCP server, how do we define two authentication? Kapil have answered that, okay?
Mayank: I've answered that. When we will create that, I will show you the authentication. Don't spam it.
Mayank: We, it depends on the type of the MCP, but again.
Mayank: I will talk about transport layer, there are HTTP kind of a one, so you have all the right ways of doing it with respect to that, okay?
Mayank: Can we say prompt will give the model better context? It will let it create, take a better action, okay?
Mayank: For example, for a planned a vacation, it had a template for prompt. Like that, how many prompt templates will it have? It can have you define the server, it is, again, defined by us, or we are using the server which is kept directly online, so we define it, okay?
Mayank: How can we know tools are available in MCP Server?
Mayank: The very first thing I told you, tools slash list is called.
Mayank: to slash list is called. That is your next part, everyone, the practical part, so don't worry.
Mayank: Teja, you have to just give me the time, because next, is actually the practical part.
Mayank: Okay, let's take my word for it. Let's take a break. In the next section, let me make it much more easier for you by showing you the practical part. And I think you will love me, because let me show you how I've defined it, okay? So, just one minute.
Mayank: Before we go on a break.
Mayank: 15 minutes nearby Yash, though I may be also happy, but in just a second, okay?
Mayank: Let me define, like, how effectively we will be seeing it.
Mayank: So, multiple ways overall, but still.
Mayank: Sweet.
Mayank: So, properly, I define each and everything, see? How the client talks, What exactly happened?
Mayank: how we get the request. So, very nicely.
Mayank: Initialized notification, everything kind of happens. Tool list.
Mayank: How it hits the tool.
Mayank: how we get all the different, different tools which are present. So, properly, step by step, I have covered each and everything.
Mayank: The complete lifecycle, architecture, this language, which is JSON RPC, Everything which they speak.
Mayank: step by step, I have spent the time to create it, so that you will know what exactly happens. See?
Mayank: So, properly, we will be having and seeing each and everything, everyone, so it will be really, really helpful. Like, step by step, actually, it will be… like, it took me a lot of time to create this in a manner.
Mayank: And, yeah, I will be showcasing you this as well.
Mayank: Cool. Ayapay Mesari kj bharakh what are the capability?
Mayank: Error codes, transport comparison.
Mayank: Real local servers, remote servers, capture commands. This, I will have to still check, but I will show you.
Mayank: Oh, I think this is more than enough. Iskelava one more file which I have created, everyone?
Mayank: Via which I will be explaining you all these things. So, this one.
Mayank: Yay, this one was a very good file, the one which I have it open. Yay, complete simulation, because this is very difficult to do.
Mayank: Yeah, Abhi, what I will do, I will open another one. I will, I will give you these files as well, don't worry. Complete thing, again.
Mayank: exactly what are the different, different servers. So don't worry, we will see each and everything right in front of us.
Mayank: what is JSON RPC, why JSON RPC? Mather, there are lots of things in MCP, though, practically abhay, but yeah, once I think we covered that, so by the end of your… end of this class only, we will have lots of things from it, okay?
Mayank: Channel. Ayush?
Mayank: 15 minutes, 10 minutes, will you share the… see, question will be answered for everyone, you know that, okay?
Mayank: You don't have to worry around that.
Mayank: MCO.
Mayank: Do you good?
Mayank: Chillo. Happy TJ's Day to everyone. We… I've missed the…
Mayank: Okay, shallow. Let's take a break.
Mayank: Cool.
Mayank: Yeah, so great, everyone.
Mayank: I think we should be able to continue.
Mayank: I hope all of you have revised, like, again, please use the time, although I think now we will be having regular classes, but still, okay?
Mayank: I will be sharing every resource, don't worry of that. First, let me explain properly, and then I will be sharing it.
Mayank: Here.
Mayank: So, just a minute…
Mayank: Amita just, fixing something.
Mayank: Sure, I'm sharing my screen, everyone let me know. Hopefully, you will be able to see the same. Cool, I hope the screen is usable.
Mayank: Perfect.
Mayank: I have this image visible, everyone?
Mayank: Any Udaymic coupon today, or not today, I didn't get the time, actually.
Mayank: Last week was pretty heavy, so I actually did not get hyped for a lot of things.
Mayank: But yeah, I will do that in the next class, okay?
Mayank: Don't worry. It's regular… last week for Rahman was pretty bad for me.
Mayank: Lots of travel, then at home, so multiple things, which should be fine, okay? Nothing you should be concerned of, so yeah.
Mayank: Food.
Mayank: I will be sharing in the lifecycle capabilities.
Mayank: So, now, everyone, I've also created one very nice notebook for you to quickly help you revise. Actually, this is just what all we have discussed, just that it will be very good for your overall revision, along with the diagrams and everything.
Mayank: In the notebook as well, I have explained you about these things, that how effectively or how exactly this thing works. So, if you will notice.
Mayank: Mcp Primitive, the three things a server can offer.
Mayank: Coming back to what's a primitive, something which I've explained to you as well, structured data AI can read, and ready-made templates, and everything. Then, how exactly the whole thing happens? Now, again, we will be seeing this in a bit in the complete MCP lifecycle approach.
Mayank: But if you will notice, the AI, it first goes to the server and says that, hey, can you give me all the tools? AI said that, hey, these are all the tools.
Mayank: Then it can directly call the tool with
Mayank: Whatever, like, is the complete, let's say, particular tool it needs to call with its argument. And then, of course, the work gets done.
Mayank: AI, when I mention here, it means the host and the client both. Ideally, you ask host, host goes to the client, client and server talk the same language, which we will come in a bit.
Mayank: Similarly, there are resources, everyone. So, resources task list, discover what's available, resource list, style guide.docs. Now, there can be, again, as I mentioned, that there can be schema.docx, any passport.pdf.
Mayank: then it can read that particular thing, get the content, and then do a lot better for those. So, resources, read-only reference data.
Mayank: Something to look at, never something that changes anything. Picture a Google Drive-connected MCP server exposing a resource for one specific file, the team style guide. The application, not the model, decide to read that resource.
Mayank: and hand it content in as context. So, answers stay consistent with how style without anyone retyping the guide every single time. So, again, if you want to
Mayank: And, there can be some guides as well as there can be some other overall resources as well, which can be useful. And your application can take the call that, hey, when do I need to have that particular resource? It does hit this resource as list.
Mayank: Similarly, there is problems, everyone. A template showed before and after, so if you will see.
Mayank: This can be a prompt definition, where it tells that, hey, if you want to do an escalation, let's do that in a structured escalation manner, so just have the name and everything.
Mayank: Okay, and if you will see issue summary, what was tried, customer sentiment, so that whatever issue you are getting, that's much better. So now what happens, everyone?
Mayank: When you will be asking for a particular role.
Mayank: It can go and read that template and then create a much better overall,
Mayank: issue in the GitHub. So, yes, still the tool will help you to create an issue, but
Mayank: Tool will not say. Tool will just have the information, so if I have, yeah, so we defined the tool like this, right? Tool will just have the information that what are the exact
Mayank: arguments I have, what I do.
Mayank: But Prompt can give you the best way of using one or multiple tools, and maybe by use case as well.
Mayank: There will be no way that Gmail will tell you that, hey, I have a send email tool.
Mayank: But prompt can have send email to manager, send email to subordinates, send email to clients, send me email to abroad, all these things, and that is where prompt will be helpful. Now, in code, how can we define it?
Mayank: although practical, we will come back a little bit later after covering lots of more things in depth. But yeah, this is exactly how you define things in Code Everyone.
Mayank: We kind of already saw for…
Mayank: the tool, so I can just print it out, like, that's the idea, when you will run it. So this was how we defined the tool, everyone.
Mayank: Then, step one addition, resource, we can refer to a particular file as well.
Mayank: Read-only nodes, so here we are now using the file… with open file handling approach.
Mayank: And prompts, so structured escalation issue summary, all these things.
Mayank: what exactly it is. So, this is how we can have the prompt.
Mayank: This, effectively, is the complete code, everyone, so this is how we define it inside of code.
Mayank: this… is the exact code, like, I can just copy the same.
Mayank: Add, say, go in here.
Mayank: To find a new file, let's say… MCP server.
Mayank: with… derivatives?
Mayank: So…
Mayank: Second, we move it here, this, effectively, everyone is the complete code, if you will notice. So, fast MCP Warm Up Server, it is having the tool, it is having the resource.
Mayank: And it is having the prompt as well.
Mayank: So, as you can see, prompt is pretty simple, like, just we are returning the complete string.
Mayank: panel, if we go and search for some common servers, like GitHub server, or sorry, Gmail…
Mayank: Gmail, server, GitHub.
Mayank: So, let's see this for the event.
Mayank: Yeah, so this is a Gmail AutoAuth MCP server, right?
Mayank: Again, there are multiple ways through which it is shown that how can you install it. That's, I think, pretty kind of easily understandable. But let's see. So, there are Docker way of starting it up and everything.
Mayank: And these are all the available tools, everyone. So, again, as I mentioned, send email tool. It tells you, like, basic email, email with attachment, and examples, and multi-part email example. So, kind of, it gives you all these things up.
Mayank: Let's see if they have created or have any resource or prompt as well.
Mayank: Because, as I mentioned, normally that is not the case.
Mayank: So, there are pre-built templates for common filtering scenario. Filter email from a specific sender, and all these things.
Mayank: Filter example, advanced source syntax, Email attachment support.
Mayank: Okay, so don't find it in a very easy-to-understand manner, let's see.
Mayank: Gmail MCP, key features.
Mayank: So, this is running.
Mayank: And yeah, I think it is having this. Try this prompt with Claude after connecting the Gmail MCP server. So, it is saying that, hey.
Mayank: if you will give this kind of a request, I am having prompts, and this is, see, how it'll happen. You will not go inside your MCP server, like, the second you have to go inside an MCP server, that is not a good server.
Mayank: It is just telling you that, hey, if you will give these kind of things, I will be able to do it a much better way, because, of course, it is having those tools ready for it.
Mayank: Okay, so if we see… source Gmail server.
Mayank: very easily, you will be able to understand, like, again, a little bit advanced. So, now, here is all the available performances which it has defined. So, see?
Mayank: Manage email, act as an email administrator, okay? So, inside it, it has actually defined the prompts and everything, and of course, all the tools will also be there. So, just showing you the real example.
Mayank: Once we complete the…
Mayank: understanding in depth, then you will be able to use the same. And actually, the reason, again, I'm going in this much depth, because I want that you can sit comfortably in an interview, be it for Google, Amazon, Uber, any of these highest of the companies.
Mayank: And then you can actually talk that, hey, I know how to create an MCP server. Because when they would be required to create an MCP server which can scale to millions or billions of users.
Mayank: Of course, it will be the case that you should know the nitty-gritty and insight out of the things, and that is where everyone in the next part, we will actually start with a complete MCP lifecycle.
Mayank: So… Even though other people, they just now start and tell you how to use the same.
Mayank: This is where we will be spending the major chunk of our time to understand how exactly it happened behind the…
Mayank: behind us, or in the backend, because this is what will be the difference between a person who knows how to just create a very basic MCP server like this, versus a person who totally, totally understand
Mayank: what effectively happens besides an MCP, and all these other different, different concepts as well. So, in the next part, let us now try to master the complete MCP lifecycle, and see where this exact MCP architecture fits in there.
Mayank: I hope that that is all clear, everyone.
Mayank: And you don't…
Mayank: Please share the link, concerning Ta.
Mayank: I see there are an area of MCP servers, Machla.
Mayank: You can find anyone, okay?
Mayank: MKHA, you will have to give me time. Kyodhana gi, I have to first explain you the theory, then go to practical. Palli bhara, it is not possible. Ki Palloli theory meh rajara explaining, that was not possible.
Mayank: So, a minute, let me add it to your craft as well, or let me…
Mayank: Simulator, I have to make it live. It's a JSX app, so let me try to fix it up, and I will make it live as well, okay?
Mayank: And, this, I think I can add. So, the notebook, everyone, I can still add.
Mayank: Yeah, notebook you are having here, okay?
Mayank: Cool.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: I will be pushing everything from in here to your G GitHub, so I think that should be helpful.
Mayank: Sure, look, great. Let us continue, everyone.
Mayank: Cool.
Mayank: See, I was trying one very, very…
Mayank: Difficult thing for all of you, but let me showcase that.
Mayank: Although we can see it,
Mayank: So I will tell you what I was trying to do.
Mayank: And why it failed, but still, we will be able to still make sense on things, so not a problem.
Mayank: Asha, one more thing, everyone. So, all this, what I'm teaching you, this is all the concepts and the architecture and complete lifecycle, which you should be aware about, and of course, I hope you're able to see the depth we are going.
Mayank: Now, recently, there was a newer version of MCP as well, which was kind of stateless in nature, but I will cover what is the benefit we get. And as of now, of course, it will take around… easily around a couple of years for that to sync up. So, we will discuss that.
Mayank: But both the versions are kind of running as of now. So it is where anything which you are learning that is not going any waste. Rather, it is helpful. Because the way these people have created the one which are using
Mayank: Tim?
Mayank: That is the level which we need to make sure that we are clearing it up, okay?
Mayank: I hope that is clear, everyone.
Mayank: Can you please again explain the MCP architecture? No.
Mayank: MCB Architect Prabhik.
Mayank: So, I've given you the notebook, everyone, like, please go through the notebook again.
Mayank: Everyone, I hope you take full advantage of these notebooks which I create for you, right?
Mayank: Okay? Yes, however, earlier version might get depreciated in future. That can be there, but that is where I think architecture is more important, because you cannot master the newer one before understanding the earlier one.
Mayank: Also, everyone, I hope there is no background noise or anything.
Mayank: So, yeah, Mike is a good investment then.
Mayank: Can you send this notebook? Ha, Mukhlab.
Mayank: As such, I can send you directly here as well, if you want.
Mayank: One minute.
Mayank: Cheer.
Mayank: What's the new one called? Nothing. It's not anything new. It's MCB architecture, just they have made it a stateless one. So, kind of building on top of what we already have.
Mayank: 90% things are same, few things they have improved, nothing else.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: Just, I'm letting you know, like, it was launched late, like, in this last week of July, so it is not that… yeah, that is now the industry standard, just…
Mayank: Making sure that you are aware of the same. But I will cover that, so don't worry. Take care.
Mayank: But now it's stateful, correct? As of now, it is there, yeah.
Mayank: Chalo, let's start.
Mayank: Okay, one minute.
Mayank: Actually, I'm just, quickly just getting the titles which I created for all of you, saying that they are helpful.
Mayank: Let's put the contact behind me here with you after a while.
Mayank: Nope.
Mayank: storage.
Mayank: Just a second, okay? Just one thing I'm trying to recollect.
Mayank: Yes, I'm trying to just get one diagram, actually, that was pretty good, the facial diagram.
Mayank: Oh.
Mayank: A bit.
Mayank: going downhill, but yeah, I think I will be able to handle it up. So, should be fine. Let's go forward.
Mayank: Perfect.
Mayank: There you go.
Mayank: Actually, I'm at my hometown, different from…
Mayank: the operation was normally where I am, so that's why I'm asking for the Noise everything.
Mayank: So, great everyone, now let's start in this particular module about understanding how MCP works beneath the complete thing which we see right in front of us, and that is actually where
Mayank: what exactly happens in the complete MCP lifecycle?
Mayank: Now, again, the same reason, covering this in depth, so we actually understand that people at Anthropic, and I guess Anthropic, over the last couple of years, have come up with some awesome engineering feeds.
Mayank: They have, of course, like, I think 10x their evaluation, billion-dollar startup, looking at one of the most expensive IPOs, etc.
Mayank: We should be understanding not only the final solution, but exactly how they reached, where they reached.
Mayank: And yes, for the same everyone, we will be now discussing about the MCP lifecycle.
Mayank: Now, again, I have created some awesome material for the same step-by-step. We will be understanding, seeing that, okay, how effectively
Mayank: A client and a server connects what exactly is the language which they speak.
Mayank: What are the different stages? And what are multiple things which happens behind the back?
Mayank: which we don't ever see, but that is what actually defines how your MCP will work. And when you are defining your own MCP server in future.
Mayank: These are actually all the things which we need to take care of, because if it fails, or if there is ever an issue.
Mayank: This kind of a simple server will not directly cut it.
Mayank: You should be aware that, okay, how exactly
Mayank: We will be creating client, we will be creating our own server, all these things should be aware, because you can sit in a way where you are either creating a client, or you are creating a server. But, yeah, that we will see after understanding this in depth. So, with that, now let's start, everyone.
Mayank: When we talk about the MCP lifecycle, there are 3 major points, or 3 major… Things which happens.
Mayank: Initialization.
Mayank: Operation.
Mayank: and the shutdown. I think the name is very, very self-explanatory in a sense. Initialization.
Mayank: Happens when we initialize the connection, so meet for the very first time, agree on a version, declare the capabilities.
Mayank: operations. What are the different, different operations which can be performed? Kind of like a handshake.
Mayank: Discover what's available, call tools, read the resources and everything.
Mayank: And finally, we can connect, close the connection, so connection can be closed from either the client or the server end. Normally, it is from the client end, where you close your, close your cloud desktop or other ways. But yeah, this is how effectively it happens. This is the official docu- diagram from the documentation, so client and server initialization phase.
Mayank: We have an initial agent request, get the response, and we get the notification as well. Then operation phase, everyone, where, again, you can call multiple tools, access all the primitives, and finally, the shutdown phase, where you can close the connection. Normally, major is the operation phase, where
Mayank: the client and the server are connected, and you can do any number of operations. You can access any primitive.
Mayank: And yeah, at the end of the day, you are just asking your host, but that is how it is happening between them. So, with that, now let's start, everyone.
Mayank: And let's start with the very first stage only. So, if you will see here, same thing. I will be referring to this along with the diagram. So, every MCP connection that has ever existed followed exactly these three stages, exactly in this order.
Mayank: Initialization is handshake and introduction. Operation is actual conversation. Shutdown is saying goodbye and leaving the room, just like real life. You can't skip straight to the conversation before anyone's ever been introduced. Very, very basic, easy analogy. And yes, if you're able to explain in this much depth in any interview.
Mayank: the person would know that, yes, this person is actually understanding the MCP and the AI thing, rather than just
Mayank: kind of using them. Because users are a lot now.
Mayank: For this MB one now, if you will notice.
Mayank: there is effectively a live demo which we can construct, so I've given the commands for
Mayank: Claude desktop, so what I have done, everyone, or what I'm trying to do in here is that…
Mayank: We are having Claude Desktop, which we will kind of be using.
Mayank: Or try to use for this particular approach.
Mayank: Although they have changed it a little bit because of how quickly things change in cloud size.
Mayank: But still, we will try to see its logs and everything, and then understand that, okay, what effectively is happening. So, what I will do, everyone, quickly, I will just have all the things set up.
Mayank: Sweet.
Mayank: No machine yet?
Mayank: MCP repolling concern. Can you please be slow, Murthy? I think I'm genuinely… Malah, I'm not in the healthcare, I can be fast today. Vivian, I hope you will be liking the speed today, right?
Mayank: Today, Suman generally not in a very good health care, I can be fast. I'm generally a little low on energy today. Normally, that is never the case, but Raj told us… I've taken, Tolo at, the Tolo 650 tablet before the class today.
Mayank: There you go.
Mayank: Shallow. Sadri haven't posted this. Abhi, manukush Nikita, I will share everything, don't worry, Teja? I will share everything, don't worry at all. First, Abhi, enjoy the in-depth explanation.
Mayank: Abhi aap kumar Zaiga, you will all enjoy it. The next Manar, you are going to love MCP, for sure.
Mayank: malar, last week, the chauh, there was no way I could have taken the class.
Mayank: So, I don't want to make… and rather than TK another, you will not have any quality problem, okay? Shalom.
Mayank: Cool. So, now, everyone, we have…
Mayank: kind of have multiple things set up. Now, I will be sharing a guide by making sure that it works with the latest version, but again.
Mayank: Claude has changed a few things.
Mayank: Ideally, you don't need to,
Mayank: do this at your end. But yes, still, if you are interested, easily you can go on Claude and ChatGP and even ask them, but let me show you what I effectively mean. See?
Mayank: Normally, whenever we are using Cloud MP1, or sorry, MCP, we just go to any application, connect it via the code or directly via, let's say, as a custom connector in here, and we are happy that, hey, my MCP will work.
Mayank: A very, very basic, simple example, which I can showcase to all of you.
Mayank: is… we can go to Langchain, and Langchain is having its MCP, so it is having MCB server.
Mayank: And in here, I can now go and go to Connectors, Add Connector, And add a custom connector.
Mayank: And I can just say, blank check.
Mayank: MCP?
Mayank: Paste the URL.
Mayank: And, in a way, I'm connected with the same. So, it is saying, no authentication.
Mayank: I think… so they have changed this as well, and I know the reason for that as well, but yeah, we can add it.
Mayank: And actually, it will be connecting now.
Mayank: So, lots of things kind of happened in the backend in this when it got connected.
Mayank: And that is what we try to, or we will understand that, how we can demystify that, okay? So, with respect to that, everyone, if you will now notice, let's try to understand the same via a little bit of logging understanding. So, if you will notice.
Mayank: Like any other application which runs, there are complete logs which are maintained.
Mayank: So, this is actually my complete logging of MCP when my… Cloud desktop runs.
Mayank: Now, let me also clarify that what all we will be mastering in this particular
Mayank: Module, because that is also very important. C.
Mayank: In the lifecycle part of given, we are discussing about the initialization phase.
Mayank: and operation and shutdown, there are multiple steps in the same as well. So, let's try to do that and understand it.
Mayank: When we talk about initialization, everyone, so let's go to the initialization part.
Mayank: And see the seat.
Mayank: Yeah.
Mayank: The server gets initialized, And, okay, let me make it a little bit bigger so y'all can read it.
Mayank: How did you open this log file? I will tell you, don't worry.
Mayank: Cool. So, I have actually set the same to make sure that you can understand it a little better, and again, I will be sharing a PDF in which all the steps, as I mentioned, will be there. For the timing, I went to this particular
Mayank: path, everyone, so I will share the path as well.
Mayank: This is the path in my machine, so user may have library logs clod mcp.log. Similarly, there is, in your Windows as well, rather, I could go to chat GPT,
Mayank: And what I can do, everyone, chat GPT.
Mayank: Where are the Claude desktop app?
Mayank: logs stored.
Mayank: in Windows and Mac.
Mayank: So, let's see this.
Mayank: It will tell you the exact path where it is stored.
Mayank: I have just got the file, see? So it is saying that… and this is the right one, okay? So as you can see, library logs claud.
Mayank: and app data, MCP logs, general MCP connections, startup errors, And, MCP server.
Mayank: by server name log, STD error output from a specific MCP server. So, very easily, it has been self-explanatory.
Mayank: And I think I can show you the file as well. Now, one thing to note, I am taking example of ClawDesktop here. It can be done by any other
Mayank: host. You can have your own VS Code, Codex, CHGPT. I am just taking it as an example from Anthropic side only. So, for that, now let's continue, everyone.
Mayank: These logs for ChatGPT MCP, still these logs available in my machine. Hello, ChatGPT app will be having this address, okay? Just a second, everyone. Background noise or any? Is there any background noise or not?
Mayank: TK again. It is there at my end, but look, I have, though, made sure key
Mayank: Very slightly, no? Teja.
Mayank: Most people will not have it. Now, the background is from my end, okay? Not from your honking, Kenav's time to close the door.
Mayank: Cool. Let's try to understand it. Yeah, very, very weird.
Mayank: And this is what I'm showing from my machine, that, okay, these are all the logs. And if you will see, there is MCP logs everywhere, MCP.log.
Mayank: There is for file system, and there is for read, write, Apple Notes, so I will come to each and every one of these things. But yeah, these are where all the logs are present, and I have taken the one MCP log file.
Mayank: Now, let's try to see exactly what happens, everyone, via this very awesome thing. See?
Mayank: The very first one is your initialization phase. So, in this simulator, you just have to press the button.
Mayank: Client speak first, version capability identity. Now, if you will notice in here, everyone.
Mayank: The client is sending a request to the server, where it's an initialization request.
Mayank: And this actually is something which it is sending, so I can close this up, or I can open it up again.
Mayank: And client is sending this kind of a request to my Son of a…
Mayank: And this is actually what I meant by the language. So when I mentioned that there is a language which is there.
Mayank: This is effectively Abhi Mandal language. So, to explain a little bit more.
Mayank: There is a concept of data layer.
Mayank: Now, when it comes to data layer, everyone, this is Actually, how?
Mayank: How?
Mayank: Client and server.
Mayank: Exchange data.
Mayank: Now, in the architectural part, I told you that how they speak the same language, and I kind of briefly mentioned that the language which they speak is JSON RPC.
Mayank: and the other 2.0 version, okay? So…
Mayank: Let's now try to understand, everyone. See, whenever two things are connecting, they need to have a way through which they can
Mayank: Share information on the data.
Mayank: It is very true for us humans as well, like, we humans normally can converse in English, Hindi.
Mayank: Any language, for that matter.
Mayank: Just that we should be aware about the rules Grammar?
Mayank: V… And everything of that particular language.
Mayank: Now, I am saying that client and server, they dock in JSON RPC 2.0 as
Mayank: I can show you in the logs as well. So, like, I will show you each and everything right in front of you, see?
Mayank: When they are initializing everyone, they are sending this information. So, if you will notice, let me close out other… every other thing.
Mayank: So this is your complete log file, which I have got, which is effectively the complete logs from my cloud. We can do it and see it right in front of us as well, but normally it has some issues, so I'm just showing you the log file which you can get.
Mayank: You will be just needing to understand it once in depth, and that would be helpful. See? Method, initialize, parameters, protocol version.
Mayank: capabilities, extension, I.O. memory context protocol, MIME types.
Mayank: text, all these things, client info, name, Cloud AI, version.
Mayank: JSON RPC 2.0 ID 0. So, if you will notice, everyone, this was exactly the message from client.
Mayank: Something which I've kind of tried to get here as well. Initialize, it is just sending which version it is.
Mayank: what might be the capabilities, but the main point is this JSON RPC 2.0. So let's try to demystify this a little bit. See?
Mayank: When we talk about JSON RPC, everyone.
Mayank: We all are kind of aware about JSON, so it is JavaScript, object.
Mayank: Notation.
Mayank: brackets in, which all of us are aware. I hope each and every one of you are aware about JSON.
Mayank: Each and every one of you are aware about JSON?
Mayank: Anyone has a need out there, JSON should be cleared.
Mayank: Formula brackets name, whatever it is, and all these things, yeah. That is your JSON thing, nothing else.
Mayank: And please be 100% focused, everyone.
Mayank: As you might be seeing, these are not the things which anyone teaches, but these are the things which you will be doing.
Mayank: to get a very, very good in-depth knowledge and best companies and everything, okay? The simple path.
Mayank: Shut up.
Mayank: Next, everyone is something known as RPC, which is… Remote Procedure.
Mayank: Procedure. Cut.
Mayank: Let me put this… remote.
Mayank: Procedure.
Mayank: Quote.
Mayank: Now, let's try to understand what effectively it helped us to do, okay? So…
Mayank: Again, it is a mixture of two things.
Mayank: 2.0 version, as of now, is working, so we are also aware that 2.0 is the version which works.
Mayank: Now, your host cannot speak this language. The reason it has a client, client connect to a server, and they both communicate in this thing. I will be showcasing you each and everything, step by step, in a manner.
Mayank: Now, let's first understand what this RPC helps you to achieve. Okay, everyone? So, when it comes to RPC,
Mayank: It… Was there a lot of soft mice?
Mayank: Or is it fine?
Mayank: Sorry about, let's… no noise, only Huana, slight honors. URL getting a lot slider.
Mayank: I'm getting it very heavy. Tyga? Chalo. No noise. Chiga.
Mayank: Excuse me.
Mayank: Hani, extremely sorry. It is… it was for Mehra, so I want to make sure.
Mayank: So, let's first try to understand what it helps you to do.
Mayank: As the name suggests, remote… procedure.
Mayank: call, okay? So, means that we will be doing something remotely.
Mayank: this… Let me get a smaller text. This… I to BC.
Mayank: allows.
Mayank: a program.
Mayank: So, any program which uses this RPC everyone, to execute.
Mayank: Execute a function.
Mayank: on another… Computer, or rather another machine. So, remote. That is where the remote part comes in. Another machine.
Mayank: As if it is local.
Mayank: abstracting.
Mayank: Thuh?
Mayank: abstracting… the details of… Transfer of data.
Mayank: An?
Mayank: Communication.
Mayank: or network.
Mayank: It helps Or… this… makes it Easy. Two.
Mayank: build.
Mayank: Search… distributed.
Mayank: applications.
Mayank: a little bit of idea. So, rather than actually we write… if you see our example, everyone, just let's try to see the VS Code and the server. So, here we have,
Mayank: let's say Query TB, right? QueryDB ABC, so something like that.
Mayank: So instead of effectively mentioning that, hey, query DB, Okay.
Mayank: 1, 2, 3?
Mayank: We can just mention, in a simple
Mayank: We can send a request to the server that, hey, please.
Mayank: query the Deb with these arguments.
Mayank: And it will take care of everything. So this is actually what JSON RPC kind of means. Let me show you from the official documentation as well, everyone.
Mayank: So, if you will go in here and ask about JS1. Art PC.
Mayank: Again, it's very, very awesome always to learn from the official documentation for any technology which I master.
Mayank: I make sure that…
Mayank: I read the complete official documentation. So, in here, now, this is… and again, we need to understand that why
Mayank: it went ahead with JSON RPC, not any other approach, so that we will also be clearing MV1C. MCP uses JSON RPC as a base message format for all client-server communication, as it is mentioned in the overview. See? Base protocol, core JSON RPC message type and everything.
Mayank: Request, we send the version, we send IT method parameters, send to initiate an operation.
Mayank: IDs must be a single number, and unique among in-flight requests, we showcase that as well.
Mayank: Either a result, where result includes result type, or an error, so it can either, like a request, it can either be a simple request, sorry, simple result, or it can error out as well.
Mayank: And yes, I think then, if you will see
Mayank: There are different, different ways. So, base protocol overview, this is the message, how it is sent. This is how we receive the reply, everyone. And if you will see, okay, what exactly it is helping us.
Mayank: It makes it easier to make remote.
Mayank: calls.
Mayank: Okay, so this is actually Being done with simplicity of… Simplicity of… GSON.
Mayank: Now, in the example part, everyone, as we have seen, so this will be our request, as an example. So, this is one request which we will be sending, or which we can send.
Mayank: And for the same, we can get a response, which can be something like this.
Mayank: Okay, well, so, yeah.
Mayank: Cool, man, so this is what you are saying, how can we believe it? Well, because I have the logs to prove it to you.
Mayank: The very first one, when we are initializing.
Mayank: we send a request to this Ride Apple Node. So, what we have done.
Mayank: my plot is connected to Apple Loads, which is also having an MCP. So it's a local MCP, okay, because Apple Lourdes are always present on my
Mayank: machine. Just think of it like any node app on Windows.
Mayank: It'll send this particular request, everyone.
Mayank: And as we can notice, it is having JSON, RPC, and an ID, which is not null, zero, or string.
Mayank: Next, everyone, we return a result.
Mayank: Where we are getting the version capabilities.
Mayank: Server info, name, version, JSON RPC 2.0.
Mayank: and this exact ID.
Mayank: So this is exactly how it happens, how effectively this is done.
Mayank: Then…
Mayank: This is the next part of the initialization phase, where also we are doing this method notification initialized.
Mayank: But what I want you to understand is that, in the data layer part, everyone, in the connection part.
Mayank: JSON RPC 2.0 is helpful. We cannot use JSON directly because it will not help us to make the remote calls.
Mayank: Our PC is having this complete information and understanding, so that it can be. You have to make sure that 2.0 is maintained, it should not be any other approach, else it will error out.
Mayank: Now, I have explained this in a little bit easier manner here as well.
Mayank: So every message in either direction shares my shape.
Mayank: Client to server request, JSON RPC, the ID, server to client, whenever it is response, JSON RPC. If it is an error, then also we get the same.
Mayank: Field, JSON RPC, always 2.0, the shared format version. ID, matches the response or error.
Mayank: Method.
Mayank: params. So, when you are making multiple calls to your server, everyone, this ID helps you to understand that, hey, when you are getting the response, because these servers
Mayank: They can send response asynchronously, and it can happen in multiple requests. The order is not same.
Mayank: This ID helped us to make sure that we are using the same.
Mayank: Now, many of you will be having the doubt that, Mayank, why are we using JSON RPC, not any other protocol? So there are multiple reasons for the same.
Mayank: The very first one, which many of you might be thinking, I guess, is around the REST API architecture, so why we are not using the REST API one.
Mayank: Well, let's first try to understand why Anthropic went with the same. The very first one, everyone is lightweight, okay? So, plain JSON, human-readable at a glance. As you can notice, it is very, very lightweight. There are actually no headers.
Mayank: know any longer kind of a spring, etc.
Mayank: Which you require, which is actually the requirement in your simple,
Mayank: JSON request, or a REST-based request, okay? So when you're making a SEO-based request, or even an XML-based request, there are lots of extra data which is sent. That is not the case in JSON RPC.
Mayank: Second, everyone is a transport agnostic. So, again, this we will discuss in a bit, when we will see the types of MCP servers, the transport layer part of it, which is your local and the remote server. So, I've kind of, again, covered it in the starting, but we will be going in depth. As an example.
Mayank: Yoda?
Mayank: Apple Notes is a local server, okay? It's a local STDIO server. I will explain to you what this STDIO is when the time will come.
Mayank: It is two-way by design, so either side can send the request. This thing is very, very important.
Mayank: And actually, one of the most important part.
Mayank: In your REST-based API, everyone, it's a one-way request, majorly. Your client can send the request to the server, but server doesn't normally send the request to the client.
Mayank: Whereas in JSON RPC, and the reason we are not going with the REST API, etc, it can go both ways.
Mayank: Your client can send the request to the server, the server can send the Same back to the…
Mayank: client, and it can also send the request as well. So, it is two ways. And notification built in, no ID, fires and expect nothing back. So, notification concept also we will learn in a bit.
Mayank: Just like HTTP has 404 and 50, JSON RPC has its own small set of standard codes. MCP inherits them all together, okay? So, again.
Mayank: MCP, or the anthropic people, everyone, they have to select a language.
Mayank: And they made sure that they are going with JSON RPC.
Mayank: not REST-based, not simple JSON.
Mayank: This is how JSON RPC handles what is there.
Mayank: This is the language which your client and your Oh, sorry. You're…
Mayank: Yeah, client and your server speaks and understands, this is how they communicate. They should be aware about this language exactly.
Mayank: And yes, this is what powers the MCP in the backend. Now, once your client and server starts their communication.
Mayank: This is how they will communicate, as I'm showing you in the logs. And further as well, everyone, these are all the advantages, like, why we went through with these things. To showcase the real one.
Mayank: As I was showing in the logs. So, this was the very first request, everyone, which was sent.
Mayank: Then this is the second request. Similarly, there's a notification initialized, so this time you don't need to send any ID, etc. Okay, so you are just sending a notification. Client is just sending a notification that, hey, I have initialized. So this is what was meant by
Mayank: Notification inbuilt.
Mayank: then message from client, message from server, then the normal thing will happen. So, this time, if you will notice, like, although this is the second part of the initialization phase, but tools list.
Mayank: And server is saying that, hey, I have all these different, different tools, but let's not get ahead in that. One more thing to note, many of us have not heard about this JSON RPC, but it is not an MCP invention.
Mayank: So JSON RPC, if we try to search, it is used in networks. JSON RPC 2.0.
Mayank: It is not connected to MCP. MCP has just picked this up directly because of the advantages which we discussed. So, when you will go on JSO RPC 2.0, it is used in multiple places. This is the complete documentation.
Mayank: I'm not sure if it's the original one, but yeah, this is the complete documentation, everyone.
Mayank: And MCP just… Or people at Anthropic who created this.
Mayank: They just thought that, hey, let's try to use JSON RPC because It is…
Mayank: pretty good in that, right? And… if you will see.
Mayank: what is RPC? Okay, it has opened the Wikipedia page only, but see?
Mayank: It's a stateless, lightweight remote procedure called protocol, primarily the specification.
Mayank: or a lightweight remote procedure called Protocol, designed to be simple, a manager of Gs or RPC Google Group. So again, it was already present.
Mayank: we are just using it via MCB. Not we, rather, but people who created this, that is the people at Anthropic, these are the ones who created the same. So, just to help you quickly, quickly summarize.
Mayank: We started by the MCP lifecycle.
Mayank: For the same, I made sure that I will be choosing Claude Desktop.
Mayank: Via the cloud desktop, I went through with logs.
Mayank: And got them out for you. Your Cloud will also be having it.
Mayank: Then, we understood that, okay, your…
Mayank: client and server, they are sending some requests. And that language, we kind of demystified that. This is known as data layer as well, the rules and the grammar and everything, and this is where we mastered JSON RPC in this particular part, which is very, very important.
Mayank: And yes, each and everything is kind of very nicely mentioned in this, that what exactly is JSON RPC, and we can easily just search. One thing to just note is this, that it is not a new invention.
Mayank: Second.
Mayank: this. What are the advantages? And why we are going through with this, and not the REST API, which we see right around you. Now, in the next part, we will try to understand and move ahead in the initialization phase, and what are the multiple steps and everything in the initialization, and see the same in the
Mayank: Practical, as well as via the logs, directly.
Mayank: ID value got changed in the locks from 0 to 1. Yes, exactly, Hardik. So, first request was for the 0 now.
Mayank: The first request got done, so next will be the IDE will be increased now?
Mayank: It was a first call.
Mayank: Second call.
Mayank: It looks like in your local… this is my local.
Mayank: Although this is how it happens in the backend, but… Yeah.
Mayank: Kulde?
Mayank: Our system server identified another system uniquely, like IP and port in case of RESTful. So this is where, again, they are connected and the host is handling this connection. If you notice.
Mayank: The host is the major entry point, right? Host starts up in client.
Mayank: And the client connects to the server.
Mayank: So, when the client sends the request, it knows that, hey, this is coming from this server, we are having an ID and everything as well. I'm taking a very simple kind of an example, and yes, then it is able to understand that, hey, this is from where the request is coming.
Mayank: This client has just sent me a request with ID 0. If I return it back with ID0, it will understand. So that is how it happens.
Mayank: Cute?
Mayank: I hope this is clear, everyone. Pretty important topic. I hope…
Mayank: Each and every one of your understanding.
Mayank: Though, from this initial complete shutdown will be same for one ID request. No, no, no, no.
Mayank: It will be different, different at best. So as you keep on moving, It will increase.
Mayank: JSON RPC, I think it started off again from here. So, the request and ID will keep on increasing as we make other calls. I think I will never go above 2 here, because I've never used it, but yes, it will keep on increasing as we move ahead.
Mayank: So, it's like, when your server starts.
Mayank: Just to make it a little bit easier.
Mayank: If I close my Cloud desktop, now when I restart it, 0, it will…
Mayank: two initialization. One, it will call and get all the tools, etc. Then, as in, when you ask it for other
Mayank: work, it will do the work for you. Yeah?
Mayank: I think the question is how the client know where to send the request, as there is no IP resolution. Nini, that is there. Matlap, again, see everyone, pay attention.
Mayank: Take me home.
Mayank: When we connect our MCPs, we are sending this server, right?
Mayank: We are sending this complete server here.
Mayank: Sihape, you will have to understand, ki, it is different from the simple… API connection.
Mayank: It is simple from the normal HTTP REST-based API connection. So just like how we give a server here, the server is given. When the client gets initialized, it takes up that server.
Mayank: And now the calls are being made. So when you are making a call, it is going back to… coming back to you with the response.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: I mean, how are you feeling? You seem to be ill. It was not related to my health, and thanks a lot, everyone, for your concern. So the emergency was not related to my health, it was other thing. My health was deteriorated this week only.
Mayank: Thank you.
Mayank: Well, I was fine, that's good, but yeah. Last week when you did have the class.
Mayank: There will be server URL, not a problem. What is the purpose of this ID? So, see,
Mayank: what happened is that, let's say that when you are initializing and sending this particular request, there can be multiple requests which we are sending, right? This ID helps us to understand that when we get back the response, okay? So let me take this up and explain it quickly. If I remove the IDs.
Mayank: How will we know that, okay, for which request was the response made?
Mayank: So it's kind of like an identifier. ID is always identifier, okay?
Mayank: What's any update for Claude Course Code. For the free course, you are saying,
Mayank: Yusme, let me… Reach out to you, Demi, I didn't get the time on this, yeah?
Mayank: So, everyone, let's move forward. I think it will then get clear, because of a co-processment.
Mayank: Oh.
Mayank: So, great everyone, now let's move forward and try to understand the complete initialization process, and what are the different, different steps. So, there are actually 3 major steps in the
Mayank: Initialization, which is your handshake, okay?
Mayank: Now, let's try to understand it. Okay. So, let's try to see them first, and then I will explain them. If I reset this complete thing, and just do it step by step.
Mayank: The very first one, everyone, which happens is that your client sends an initialized request to your server. So, JSON RPC 2.0 ID1, initialize.
Mayank: Multiple parameters and multiple things it can send, dependent on what kind of,
Mayank: The way it is getting connected.
Mayank: But the very first one, everyone, is this simple initialize, here's the version and everything. So the client sends it to your server, both are happy.
Mayank: Second, everyone, your server sends it back to the client that, hey, I am having this protocol version, you send me with the ID one.
Mayank: I'm returning with ID 1, because, again, see, server can get multiple requests from this client, right? Server can send in future multiple requests when it is doing anything with parallelization. So this ID helps us to pinpoint that, yeah, this request is coming for this particular thing.
Mayank: Now, this protocol version should also be…
Mayank: Like, again, there is an approach where we check the capability.
Mayank: Of the version, so we will come to that, okay?
Mayank: So, client said that, hey, this is my initialization call, with ID1.
Mayank: server said that, okay, for your ID1 request only, I'm telling you that I have the protocol version, I have the tools.
Mayank: What is my server name and everything?
Mayank: Next, everyone, we just have an initialized notification. So, here, no ID, anything.
Mayank: Client just tell to the server, kith, I am able to support you, I support you the same thing, and we have been initialized. So, these are the three steps, everyone.
Mayank: The clients speak first, sending exactly 3 things.
Mayank: JSON RPC ID, method initialized. Parameters, what is the version?
Mayank: Capabilities, client info, okay?
Mayank: Server answers matching the same ID, with its own three things.
Mayank: result, protocol version. So these versions should be compatible. It should not that the server is kept on
Mayank: 2023 version, and the client is on the latest version. Like, there are, again, by dates, there are versions which are compatible.
Mayank: If you'd rather go on the official documentation, you will see different, different things, okay? So it can happen that this 251125 is compatible with the
Mayank: Last three, maybe, or last 2.
Mayank: The latest one will, of course, be compatible with at least the last two or last, last three or last two. Maybe it is not compatible with this very initial one, okay?
Mayank: And now, again, it is just giving that, okay, I have the capabilities of tool. My name is Recipe Box, so again, your server will have a name, Gmail and CP Server. You can name your server, right? A very good example, we created a server here. We gave it the name Warm Up Server.
Mayank: So, that is what the name is. And the next step, client steals the handshake with a notification, seals the handshake with a notification, no reply expected. This was, one of the part of
Mayank: RPC.
Mayank: It is not possible in a simple REST call. In the rest call, when you send a request, you always get the response. Here, it's all fine.
Mayank: It is no ID, nothing, it is just responding that, hey, I have made the connection, not a problem. There are two major rules. Client should not send anything but a ping before the server responds to initialize, so again, we'll discuss what the ping is, it is mentioned here.
Mayank: Server should not send anything but a ping or log 9 before receiving initialized. So again, we will discuss about this ping, but this is just for the connection check that, yes, everything is happening.
Mayank: The whole idea is that your client and server, they should be very, very nicely connected.
Mayank: Your host can never connect with the server?
Mayank: Client and server do these three steps when they are getting initialized.
Mayank: Once you do these two steps, that is where it will be totally… Sealed.
Mayank: That, hey, we have done the complete approach.
Mayank: Now, for the same everyone, this is exactly the official documentation. I can just have the… Tight mode.
Mayank: So, see, initialization must be the first interaction between client and server during this phase.
Mayank: Established protocol version compatibility, the very first one. Exchange and negotiate capabilities, share implementation details. The client must initiate this phase by sending an initialized request containing protocol version and all these things, which we saw right in front of us.
Mayank: The server must respond with its own capabilities and information, so what exactly it is.
Mayank: Does it support prompt? Does it support resources? Does it support tools?
Mayank: After successful initialization, The client must send an initialized notification to indicate it is ready to begin normal operation.
Mayank: So, client actually tells that, hey.
Mayank: I am all good, we can start. We are now connected. And these are the things. As I mentioned, I will come to the ping part in a bit, so that is something which we need to understand as well, but yeah. This is the complete, complete process of your initial connection, everyone.
Mayank: Which happens?
Mayank: And in this, as of now.
Mayank: And this is actually what happens when your Cloud desktop gets start as well.
Mayank: Initially, it just makes sure that every MCP It is connecting to.
Mayank: Or it wants to connect.
Mayank: It knows that, yes, it is active.
Mayank: If, by any chance, any MCP is down, and this is a very good reason, now you will be able to connect to many things, pay attention.
Mayank: If I go onto connectors, you will see this Warning sign.
Mayank: Because some connector, it is not able to understand. Maybe the authorization have expired, but yes, it is not able to make the connection. The reason it is able to pick a tick in front of all the other everyone is because it did this initialization.
Mayank: It is aware at the starting.
Mayank: So, even though I have not used Nitin, it is still telling me from that backend logs that, hey.
Mayank: I am facing some issue in this, please check it out.
Mayank: So that is the exact, exact reason, everyone, you see this slash one here.
Mayank: Because when it would have tried to connect
Mayank: maybe due to authorization or any reason, the server might have even died down or anything. It was not able to get the response back, and that is how your complete thing is aware that, yeah, this is what happens.
Mayank: Weird, everyone?
Mayank: I hope the same is clear, very much in depth.
Mayank: Right in front of you.
Mayank: enjoying, in depth. What is this change in the initialized request? Like, again, that…
Mayank: It is just… you can assume that, yes, I am having these tools, nothing else.
Mayank: The pink part, you will be explaining later, haha, in a bit. Okay?
Mayank: Can you show the complete server response during initialize about? Include all the information, like tools and resources? So, that is the next part, Rakesh. I cannot show that as of now. Take care.
Mayank: Abhi cannot show that.
Mayank: That is the next part in the operation phase.
Mayank: The very, very first part in the operation phase, that is where it comes.
Mayank: why the two-way communication is needed? We will be communicating in a request-response format, right? Why a server needs to call a client. So Gopi Krishna, just think about a request where it takes a lot of time.
Mayank: So, your server will then tell the client that, hey, this is how much it has been completed. This is the current sequence. So, don't you think that server should also be able to send the client request then?
Mayank: Rather than client asking that, hey, what is the status, what is the status? Rather than just that polling thing.
Mayank: Clear?
Mayank: Can it replace WebSocket?
Mayank: Honestly, I will have to check that, like, cannot comment that, okay?
Mayank: Nikita again, Deku, there are multiple examples, sorry, positives and benefits of everything.
Mayank: Could… have we done WebSocket here? I don't think WebSocket is required.
Mayank: Because WebSocket is a constant connection, okay? So I don't think it is required. That would have been overdue.
Mayank: In the first part, only connection is established. Exactly, exactly.
Mayank: This is what I'm showing you.
Mayank: This is genuinely the exact thing, nothing else. Exactly.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: But yeah, client is for connection purpose only, then what is the role of capabilities?
Mayank: Should not be a server's property only?
Mayank: What do you mean by capabilities, or primitives, or what?
Mayank: This capability you are saying, root list, changed.
Mayank: Server is also mentioning, like, what all I can do. Server should also… Sorry, clients should also be able to tell, I think, go back here.
Mayank: This might be a better one, Abhi, if I show you.
Mayank: Initialization.
Mayank: So, it should also tell key what all it supports, sampling, elicitation, task, what all it can do. So, it also tells that, hey, I am having these much capabilities. Just search for it on Mayank GPT, or ChatGPT, that's what it is.
Mayank: I know, but I don't want to go in.ki.
Mayank: In an interview, you are at the top, okay?
Mayank: it is not a constant connection that how it sends requests back and forth. Jaikar,
Mayank: Thodassar read about the connection part.
Mayank: As of when we have API, this is not a constant connection, but we are able to send the request and response, right?
Mayank: But can't this switch can be done through some async check, same as cron call types of server response takes time?
Mayank: No.
Mayank: Again, basic of the connection and networking, everyone.
Mayank: In an async, The connection is open.
Mayank: In this, you send a request, you forget about it.
Mayank: Server can tell you that this is happening, because it's a two-way communication.
Mayank: Asynchronous is when the work is happening in the backend. Okay?
Mayank: Now, because I'm going in-depth, so you will have to read about these things, because these are not easy. Do you ever go to the second page of documentation, everyone?
Mayank: Second page, I meant here. See where I'm going. I'm going to the specification, then, in this lifecycle.
Mayank: Teja?
Mayank: I hope you do understand, Key. To understand this, it will be a little difficult and everything, right?
Mayank: Yes or no?
Mayank: But I hope you're enjoying it. I love MCP. Mhodi, the idea is that once you understand MCP in this much depth, using is very easy. Using is not a problem.
Mayank: Hello. Let's move forward, everyone.
Mayank: And this, I will share, this is, like, gold mine. Believe me, this is gold mine.
Mayank: Mallam.
Mayank: honestly, I have to sit for around 3-4 hours, get all my notes, tell it to…
Mayank: Which I use here. Cloud only. Cloud code.
Mayank: This is how I need you to cover it. This is exactly how I want you to cover it.
Mayank: I gave… actually, I copied all these things, made my limit over.
Mayank: But finally, thankfully, I was able to get this thing up. This I will share with all of you, don't worry, but this is genuinely goldmine.
Mayank: Well, if in an interview, anything around MCP starts, and you explain in this much depth.
Mayank: The person would be like Hita. If he understands MCP, then he will be aware about other things as well. Tyga?
Mayank: Cholo, let's move forward.
Mayank: How to open this tool from to get this? I will be sharing you this. You can open it rightly in your PC.
Mayank: Channel.
Mayank: So, great everyone. Now, with that, let's move forward and continue our discussion. Once the same has been done, the next part which comes in before we jump onto the operation phases, are these two things.
Mayank: Version and capability negotiation.
Mayank: So, let's try to understand the same as well from the documentation. So, we have already seen that in the initialization part, everyone.
Mayank: What exactly happened is that?
Mayank: The… Client sends that what all it can support, what protocol version it is, and everything.
Mayank: Then, what happens, everyone, is that…
Mayank: The server also responds that, hey, this is what is it, I am having…
Mayank: prompts, I'm having resources, I'm having tools, you can subscribe to the resources if you want, so the capabilities and everything.
Mayank: But, just… Communicating this thing is not important.
Mayank: This is, like, the very, very first check. After that.
Mayank: version negotiation and everything also happens, so see?
Mayank: In the initialization request, the client must send a protocol version it supports.
Mayank: This should be the latest version supported by the file.
Mayank: If the server supports the protocol version, it must respond with the same version.
Mayank: Otherwise, the server must respond with another protocol version it supports. This should be the latest supported by the server.
Mayank: If the client does not support the version in the response, it should disconnect. So, very, very simple and easy to understand with analogy.
Mayank: See, effectively, when they communicate, they are saying that, hey, see, this is the version I saw.
Mayank: Server will also respond back with the server version it supports, in worst case, if they are not compatible.
Mayank: they will disconnect, which I think makes a lot of sense. It is exactly like you ask someone that, hey, like, let's say you are in a, maybe, fair or anywhere.
Mayank: You ask the person in a conference, you ask the person which language you speak. Or maybe not language, let's try to make it with the department. Hey, are you from tech?
Mayank: The person says, no. Or, you are looking for someone who works at… in the AI space, the person works in the finance space. You will disconnect.
Mayank: Totally, initially, only you will disconnect, because if the version compatibility is not supported.
Mayank: the… they both cannot work together. So, in that case, everyone, version negotiation, what actually happens when client and server don't agree.
Mayank: If they don't agree, for the very first time. See, in the very first call, everyone.
Mayank: Client sent the latest version.
Mayank: Server send the latest version. If they don't agree, then they send the list of version which they support.
Mayank: And now, again, they will check.
Mayank: If it is supported, then you will move forward. If not, then you will disconnect. Now, one thing to note here, why this is important, because tomorrow, when you create your own client safety one.
Mayank: Which, again, will be required in a very big company.
Mayank: you will have to make sure that you are only connected to the right servers. And it can very well happen that, example, in Claude, as of now.
Mayank: Very, very easily.
Mayank: Claude cannot connect with multiple servers, and we will see the error for the save as well.
Mayank: Just as an example, if I go on GitHub, everyone.
Mayank: And if I have, let's say, Gmail MCP server, GitHub?
Mayank: This MCP server is not being maintained, so it was archived on, let's say, March 3rd, 2026.
Mayank: So, it may very well happen that this is not on a version which Claude may support now.
Mayank: So if it doesn't support, it will not be the best approach. So this is the level of knowledge you should be aware, so that you can create your own MCP
Mayank: servers and clients in future, that yes, they should be supporting each other, and this is very much valid, it's like.
Mayank: A very good example of this, WhatsApp.
Mayank: If…
Mayank: many of you must have seen the error that WhatsApp latest version will see the deleted thing, the message will be deleted on the latest version of WhatsApp for everyone. So they should support each other. So this is where the version negotiation happens.
Mayank: They make sure.
Mayank: And this is, again, the information which
Mayank: When you define your client and the server, the exact
Mayank: Version on which you create them.
Mayank: This is where it is kind of…
Mayank: encoded in the DNA of the server and the client. So when we defined our client and the server, because in MCP, we will be defining these two only, right?
Mayank: They are told that, hey, this is the exact version which you support.
Mayank: And… now?
Mayank: your server should also support it. Now, Mayank, what does this mean by support? Well, see.
Mayank: When it happens with respect to support, I can go and show you the key changes.
Mayank: For example, in this version, there were few changes.
Mayank: Okay, few changes were… few things were deleted, few were kept. So, if there is something which you are not handling, as a very good example, let's say that you say that, Mayanka support all the versions.
Mayank: Well, if you're… Client will support all the versions.
Mayank: From the server.
Mayank: Then you should make sure that you are handling everything, even from the very initial version.
Mayank: what all kept on changing, what all kept on changing and getting added. You should support each and everything. Your data models and everything inside your client.
Mayank: Should be supporting each and everything in healthcare.
Mayank: So that is the level of thing that you as a client devil will do. So, a very good question in Google interview can be that, hey, you are sitting in an interview.
Mayank: The interviewer can ask you. You have to create an MCP client.
Mayank: which supports 2 years old MCP servers as well. And if you say that, hey, I will just connect it with the MCP
Mayank: URL, that is where you will never know that why you got rejected, but yeah, this exactly is where the software development part of it is coming through.
Mayank: So this, everyone is exactly the version negotiation. So, in here, they are on the supported version, so that is all good. If not, they must have negotiated that, hey, I support all these versions. Server would have said that, hey, I have all these versions. If there is a mis… there is a match, they will move forward, else they will quickly disconnect.
Mayank: Which, as I mentioned, kind of seems very logical. So, virtual negotiation isn't a retry loop.
Mayank: In exactly one counteroffer. Checked exactly one, with disconnect as the only fallback.
Mayank: So it will not that, hey, you will tell that, hey, I support this, can you fix this? No, no, no.
Mayank: It is just that I support all these versions, you tell me your versions. If we are compatible, we will connect, else we will disconnect. So this is exactly how the version negotiation happens, everyone.
Mayank: Now, let's try to move on to the next one, which is going to be around the capability negotiation.
Mayank: If it disconnect, what will be the next step? No, you cannot use the MCB server.
Mayank: That simple.
Mayank: Do client need to update the version when server stops supporting the version used during the initialization phase? Yes.
Mayank: Actually, it's the other way around.
Mayank: Okay, Suzie, as of now, Amit, I hope you do understand key b for us.
Mayank: Client is a very black box, but when we will be creating it, so we will… we have to demystify that black box. So these are all the things which will be
Mayank: There in that, okay?
Mayank: Kulk, any other doubt, anyone?
Mayank: Okay, are we good to move forward?
Mayank: Every time you need to maintain version Nike, it is not for maintaining.
Mayank: It is of making sure that anything which is introduced in the newer version, it is supported.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: It is not that key, maintained, like, just as a very good example I will give you.
Mayank: Windows is a very good example. If you have created any application on Windows 7, it will work on Windows 11 as well, everyone, right or wrong.
Mayank: Windows 7 to Windows 11, Windows XP as well.
Mayank: Because that… Windows, okay? It supports the previous application as well. It is not
Mayank: Moved away. Tohapi is Sema Jayla. Windows and software value analogy is pretty good. Thinka?
Mayank: When the client send the timeout request, our timeout is there, Machla. Can we use tool-related middleware with MCP tools?
Mayank: Nayanab can get the question, Shubhuba.
Mayank: Is there any agreed, Norm, like, to support the version? Nothing like that? Just, server is created with some version, it will be compatible. Client will be saying that, hey, these are the ones I support.
Mayank: Match, don't think anything.
Mayank: We will learn how to make clients, huh? You will learn how to make clients.
Mayank: Mahab, again, have you seen anyone talk about MCB in this much depth?
Mayank: Are you able to see why I'm talking in this much depth?
Mayank: We will define them as well, not a problem. Who proposed supported version client or server? No, no, when you define your client, see, Nikko, again, it's me, you have to understand one thing.
Mayank: It is on you, the developers.
Mayank: Okay? It is genuinely on you on developer's part.
Mayank: When you are creating a client, you will make Shokibh
Mayank: whatever was there in the previous version, I should… should I support it or not?
Mayank: Should I support it or not?
Mayank: And vice versa on the server end as well.
Mayank: So… Again, Windows and software is a very good example. Let's say that you are making a new software.
Mayank: It is on you, should you support Windows 7 or Windows 8 or not. Make sense, everyone?
Mayank: Okay, but if you're creating a software.
Mayank: It is on you, if you're supporting Windows 7 or Windows XP or not, right?
Mayank: At the same time, when you are creating a client, which is your Windows, let's say Windows 11,
Mayank: Now, again, it is on you if you are supporting Windows XP or 7 softwares. Are you having those files, those kernels, those other things?
Mayank: So it is both ways.
Mayank: Sumanjugai?
Mayank: I hope that is clear.
Mayank: Connection is ejected, so you cannot work together. Connection ejected means key, TK? You cannot use the MCP.
Mayank: Make sense?
Mayank: Does all this happen sequentially, and all are compulsory, huh? It is compulsory, it happens sequentially.
Mayank: It is required.
Mayank: My new camera? A little tired today, so… and as I mentioned, like, I'm also not well, personally, I don't want to see you, my… I want you to see my…
Mayank: Sick Chapel.
Mayank: There you go.
Mayank: Any other doubt, anyone? Nhu De Devesh meh, please, it is required.
Mayank: If the version is not supported, then how do we upgrade to supported version? Development, we will go back and see, kibahi, what is the exact thing we have to develop now.
Mayank: That is how it happens, right, everyone?
Mayank: Pallop, I hope all of you must have seen some softwares which are not supported, then people develop and do a crack around it, and then they do that. For example, I will tell you a very good example and explain. You see.
Mayank: You see that in this? Everyone, what are the major versions, major changes?
Mayank: Enhance allows servers to expose icon as additional metadata for tools.
Mayank: Teja?
Mayank: Add to support calling via sampling. A big cheese bun, or just tell me one thing, everybody.
Mayank: Everything.
Mayank: Tool calling support to sampling via tools and everything.
Mayank: Add support for URL mode elicitation.
Mayank: Now, if this feature, if this feature… Is…
Mayank: something which you want to use, but your server doesn't support it. So you will not be able to, of course, do that, else you will have to handle it.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: So many of them will be breaking changes as well.
Mayank: Hannah?
Mayank: Why you have answered to any type of question? If you will not have answered to any type of question, then I will be a bad maternity Yashman?
Mayank: So that's a good thing. How I have answered to every kind of question.
Mayank: I should have known.
Mayank: If something is there which I don't know, I say that I don't know.
Mayank: But otherwise, yeah, the answer, why I have an answer, because I read these things over the… why I read the documentation. I spend that time.
Mayank: You go?
Mayank: It is not needed to communicate on which particular version finally they get off. It's very simple, see? They should have a common version, just that, nothing else. Which is very, very logical, but let's think about it now.
Mayank: They should have a common version, nothing else.
Mayank: Bhi, if you are having a Windows, and if you're having a software, don't you think they both should support it?
Mayank: Can you run Windows?
Mayank: Gta V on Windows XP.
Mayank: Can you run GTA V on Windows XP, yes or no?
Mayank: Yes or no?
Mayank: GTA V on Windows XP?
Mayank: Bhad, please chat me. Madh Bolajna. Nay, right?
Mayank: Do you guys have a quality question?
Mayank: So just let me ask you one more question. Can you run Windows game on Mac?
Mayank: Can you run Windows game on Mac?
Mayank: Nay, but akh mehi U tab.
Mayank: up there it is.
Mayank: Cross.
Mayank: Rhodes, Mac, Windows, gaming. So, it is not supported by default, but
Mayank: Mac, Windows Gaming, what was the name of the application?
Mayank: Paddles is there. So what it does is change that particular codes and everything which is happening, so you can run Windows game on machine. So that is how we fix it, right? Development comes into picture.
Mayank: So, version 1 AHZ, version negotiation is very simple in that ways, right? Well, there will be some things, no?
Mayank: Either if it is not supported, then go back to development.
Mayank: How many classes we will have for MCP also? Can we get the complete sapers for this course? OQ, Oki, PatilNet…
Mayank: Your name is difficult to pronounce. Two more classes, I guess. 2, 3, Malhavik, I'm taking it in depth here. Mhab, let me know. If any one of you have any concern with anything which I'm teaching, reach out to me on the email. Otherwise, I have told you my philosophy. I'm making you ready for the next 2-3 years, not just for the next, policies, I will be really honest.
Mayank: If you think that you will get the best interest of the job.
Mayank: By having a basic idea, I'm extremely sorry, it will not be the case. I genuinely have friends
Mayank: who are earning 60, 70 LPS plus, I know the level at which they are. Take care.
Mayank: Generally, they know these things in depth. Acha, one more thing.
Mayank: If people are still there for 4 to 7 years of experience, please send me your email, please send me your CVs.
Mayank: Because the person is still looking. Are two people from your… Badge?
Mayank: has been leashed out by the percentage.
Mayank: Cool?
Mayank: Madhavib why I'm going in depth. It is very easy for me here, MCP, Paneman vaibhavila spent so much time, go all the documentation. I can say that, hey, MCP, connect everything, Kyle. Anything for 15 plus,
Mayank: I might have. Let me connect with the person I met. If he required, I will tell you, yeah?
Mayank: So, yeah, cool, I think… Can you see my messages? Arti reaching you? Harp Priya? They are reaching me. If they were related to concept, I must have talked and everything. Shaol.
Mayank: Should we move forward and discuss about the capability negotiation, or do it tomorrow?
Mayank: Sir khaly Kartha, because I know it will be overload.
Mayank: Yeah, and it is overloaded at my end as well on Mujajkhas bin in here, so… Belgarte.
Mayank: Extremely sorry. I know normally I'm the one pushing it, but Abhi told us, time.
Mayank: Hell.
Mayank: version rah. Tyga?
Mayank: I think when I'm just playing somewhat.
Mayank: I will be sharing all the files, don't worry.
Mayank: Next concept was capability negotiation, then we would have done two operations.
Mayank: Uskeh baj, we would have talked about shutdown.
Mayank: In that only, we would have discussed about transport layer.
Mayank: So, STDIO and HTTP1. HTTPSC is now discontinued, but I will still teach you that.
Mayank: And, bus, yeah, these were the major things.
Mayank: Uskebad, you know MCP in a lot more detail than anyone else. Uskebhad is just some, way of using it.
Mayank: Via Claude, via code, doing it. I might be doing it directly via code.
Mayank: And if the time permits, I will show you how to push it on pip, this, so that your MCP servers are shareable in a Docker and everything.
Mayank: Else, you will know how to use and create them. The client and the server, you will know how to create them, that is a major push, yeah?
Mayank: Ciao.
Mayank: Cool.
Mayank: Coupon I will coupon next time, everyone. Joby coupons I will give next time. Kaj will try Karthong bah.
Mayank: I will share everything. Teja, throw us a time, I will share. Give me time till 3 or 4 o'clock, I will share everything. Any doubt, anyone?
Mayank: Will the project include all this?
Mayank: Naikum, project, Mehna, we will be creating client when required. Though, you will be needing this level of tetra.
Mayank: When you will be getting the dev. When you will teach A2A protocol, I will teach A2A protocol.
Mayank: Basics bhad Devesh Mohenge, don't worry at all. Chalo. Cool. How was today's class, everyone?
Mayank: How was the today's class? Again, extremely sorry for the last week. The totally was not in my hand, and this week we're away, so I should be fine. Yeah.
Mayank: Happy Teja's Day, everyone. I learn a lot from you than you do from me.
Mayank: Then, again, if I missed out on any question, please raise your hand and I will clear it out. Just will be taking a little list out today. I have to attend something.
Mayank: At home, the reason there was an obvious last week. So yeah, Teja.
Mayank: Sahel, Ramesh Shram, Hardik, Debayan Gopi. Sahel, I think you mailed to me, I replied to your email, just check once.
Rameswar: Hello?
Mayank: Sahail, Ramesh, we will go via the queue. Sahel, you were first.
sahilthapar: Yeah, so thank you for replying to my email, but you had asked me to ask this question here. I am looking to do your Claude certification course, Claudevane 1. The question is,
sahilthapar: Would you be covering them here, or how is, like, because I want to prepare for the Cloud Code certification.
Mayank: I will be honest in this with every one of you.
Mayank: It will take time here. Claude, certification KLA, I created the content.
Mayank: But they changed it to 4 things now, 4 routes.
Mayank: Deca?
sahilthapar: Okay.
Mayank: I'm not sure if you're aware about it. I will be creating the content for it, and I will be uploading it on the course on Udemy, but what I will do, I will give all of you access to it either via YouTube, so you don't have to pay or purchase it unnecessarily.
Mayank: I will be either uploading it to your course in the Krishnet Academy, or give you access on YouTube.
Mayank: I will just explain, like, what I'm planning to do. So I have good plans for that as well. If you will now search Lot Certification, and this is for everyone.
Mayank: And this will take me around 2-3 weeks. I had planned to do it last week on SD, but Teja last week, Together.
Mayank: But, see, they have now divided it into four.
Mayank: earlier it was just this CCAF, so I created the content for this, but kind of it has been obsolete.
Mayank: That said, what I have taught in my YouTube on Claude Code, that is where lots of people are able to crack the course, because certification.
Mayank: Because, again, it is very much in-depth, but for the particular these things.
Mayank: just give me 2-3-4 weeks by maybe this September month, and I will create it. I will update it on the Udemy course as well, and I will give you all free of cost. Like, I don't want that if you are connected with me.
Mayank: For any of my content which I should teach you, you should be unnecessarily purchasing the course. Teja? So, I will give you that. Uske bhadam assured, ki malab, if you study it properly, you will be able to clear it out. Teja?
sahilthapar: So basically, Udemy and the one which you will upload, both of them, right?
Mayank: Udaymi Kara cannot promise, because they are…
Mayank: Malabho, same content with Yadhwa, I will give the same content, so you don't.
sahilthapar: Okay, got it.
Mayank: Well, look, my idea is to give you the contender, not, like, cars and will wear, so that…
sahilthapar: Take, tick, tick. Thank you, sir, thank you so much.
Mayank: So, save your manu this particular.
Mayank: Venomish?
Rameswar: Hello, am I audible?
Rameswar: Hello?
Mayank: Yes, yes, I'm sure you're audible.
Rameswar: Okay, so, I have a question that, how this MCP…
Rameswar: version 2, you know, two-way communication happens without IP and,
Rameswar: quote, I think it is not possible for anyone to
Mayank: Workday?
Rameswar: So maybe it doesn'.
Mayank: server host, it is able to get that IP address and everything, right?
Rameswar: I'm not able to hear you.
Mayank: When I, can you check your internet once?
Mayank: I'm saying that when I connect to a server, it gets that IP and everything, whatever it requires to connect.
Rameswar: Yes, so, IP… so there has to be… so how this, you know, server recognizes the client? You told that, a server recognizes the client by IDs, but, internally, there has to be some mechanism where the…
Mayank: last night.
Rameswar: These are mapped… are mapped with, IP and port.
Rameswar: Of different…
Mayank: All that thing is taken care internally, Mithlav. See, what happens that, when you are having your host, you are using your cloud.
Mayank: Claude picks, spuns up a client, that client connects to the
Mayank: Connects to that particular server.
Mayank: Abh, now they do maintain those IDs and everything in the backend. Yale ID, either these things were there, so all those things are what they maintain, and that is how the connection happens. So that is just like how any other connection gets connected.
Mayank: TK just that, there are two transport layers. SUSME, in the backend, all that is maintained, but if we want, we can go in depth of that.
Mayank: I honestly did not get.
Rameswar: No, no, is there any SDK… is there any SDK that will be given to us to, you know, develop this MCP?
Mayank: There is… there are anthropic official SDK as well, if you want, MCP SDK, there is Fast MCP, Fast MCP.
Mayank: Via which they will be handling all these inputs. There are these things with which.
Rameswar: So, if I have an email of my own, if I have an email…
Rameswar: address, like, Gmail or Yahoo. I have my own email address, like Nik.in. Then, how should I develop, MCP, you know, compatible my, domain? How could I make my domain MCP compatible?
Mayank: Nini, again, view create an MCP server.
Mayank: It is not like a… it is a link… it is not like Google.com is MCP, no, no, no.
Mayank: Okay, let me explain it in a little bit easier way. See?
Mayank: So… We are having… Like, for example, when I copied this from here, or copper MCP server.
Mayank: If I paste it here. This is their MCP server.
Mayank: Okay, so see? This is having everything. It gets from this, and this is how it gets predicted.
Mayank: So, now, it is not that keyword making Google.com MCP compatible. This is just having this information so it can connect. Once it connects, then it can do all the action, so you create your normal MCP server, nothing else.
Mayank: Here you go?
Mayank: Now, that server gets connected to the client, and normally via the client-server architecture, the way everything happens, it happens. Just that it is having JSON RPC as their language, not the simple JSON, HTTP, JSON REST one.
Mayank: So, what sara Gasara happened in the backend? Like, just as an example, if when I go to Google.
Mayank: Google.com, right?
Mayank: when I ask it something?
Mayank: Of course, Google knows that it is connecting with me. It knows that, okay, I have to request a return to this, even though I'm reaching out to Google.com, because in the backend, it knows all these other things as well, which is a part of any client-server connection, right?
Rameswar: So, basically, basically, if I am a service provider like Gmail or something like that, then I have to create a MCP server.
Mayank: Yes, if you want your application to be used within the AI, within the host of other AI applications, then you will have to create an MCP server.
Rameswar: Okay, so that MCP server will… and who is going to create that MCP server's client protocols?
Rameswar: Means client-side is going to be developed by whom? It will be developed by other developers?
Mayank: It will be developed by… developed by the…
Mayank: application on which it will run. Like, for example, for Claude.
Mayank: Anthropic people will develop the client side here, so that when I'm going here and I'm adding it.
Rameswar: So…
Mayank: it should always be updated, it should support that, yeah, I can add these connectors. So, this was developed by Anthropic, this is Climate.
Rameswar: So these connectors are developed by, Anthropic, developers.
Mayank: Yeah.
Rameswar: the, the, the Gmail and,
Mayank: Nadeem?
Rameswar: Nadeem…
Mayank: These are survivors. These are said advice.
Rameswar: These are servers. So, who has developed these connectors?
Mayank: So these are being developed by the companies only, who are owning it. For example, the Gmail one has been developed by Google.
Rameswar: Yes.
Mayank: Gmail one has been developed by Google. If I go on new details, Rated by Roman.
Rameswar: Open.
Mayank: I will make it a little easier for you, pay attention.
Mayank: Awesome.
Mayank: Sweet.
Mayank: You just create MCP server.
Mayank: Of your application.
Mayank: Okay.
Rameswar: Punishments.
Mayank: And there is… host.
Mayank: Host, ideally, is host.
Mayank: which has an AI access.
Mayank: Skika?
Rameswar: Understood.
Mayank: So it is having an AICS. Now, they will create service. Sorry, host, client. They will create clients.
Mayank: They will handle all these things. Well, it is pretty easy now, MCP client, via libraries and everything, they will get this client.
Mayank: And they will be compatible in these, so they can connect with your servers. So you will be maintaining the servers.
Mayank: For example, Anthropic people, they maintain that, hey, we will handle this client creation. When you want to connect to a server, we will ping… we will have a client, and it will connect to it. So, simple client-server architecture, nothing else.
Rameswar: Understood. So the client side will be developed by the host, and the MCC.
Mayank: Most will take care of the client.
Rameswar: Post will take care of us. Understood. Thank you.
Mayank: You… if you… if you are on the host side now, it depends on which equation you are setting. If you are on the host side, then you will develop the client thing. Well, for example, Anthropic people will now make sure my client is sending all the things which is required. If you're on the server and server, you will define server.
Rameswar: Understood, understood.
Rameswar: Thank you.
Mayank: Tk… One minute… Desai Meh Shram.
Mayank: Hardik, you are next.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, he hi, man.
Mayank: Right.
Hardik Vora: Thanks for explaining in detail, appreciated the diagrams and all. Quick couple of questions, Mayank. So, earlier, when we were discussing in the doubt clearing session, right, that there will be multiple client IDs, as we… it is a black box for us.
Mayank: I have to understand that, I didn't.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, you can… you can check it.
Mayank: I will be checking it up.
Mayank: Let me see, Mahab. But, TK let me check it, but I will be able to do it. Let me try it today else, I will do it by next class, actually.
Hardik Vora: Sure, sure. That will help, understand that.
Mayank: How do you know that it's a simple client-server architecture, Machla? It is just that easy we are connected to any server using Postman.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank: At the end of the day, we have this backend thing kiabayh, we know k postman k karst response,
Mayank: So, it is simple client-server architecture, Kusha is very simple in that ways.
Hardik Vora: Okay. Second question is, Mayank, in parallelism, you mentioned, right? So…
Hardik Vora: Just in… as per your earlier examples, I mean, I have to connect to, send an email.
Hardik Vora: To edit an email, and then to send it to my manager, with a subject, with a body as a sick leave and all.
Hardik Vora: The earlier example which we were mentioning, right?
Hardik Vora: So here, how many clients will get, called? Because there are multiple actions in a user request.
Mayank: So, if there are multiple actions when you give a request.
Mayank: Now, your server will be connected to a single client TK.
Mayank: Now, what will happen, it will actually depend on what is the logical flow of the option which you're,
Mayank: this feels like this, your AI feels like.
Mayank: It can batch the request. For example, in a single request, it can add, ask it to get, and edit an email, maybe. Okay? So a single client, it will be a single client only.
Mayank: It can send the batch request, it can, make sure that it can do it one by one, if you need to first get it, then draft it, then edit. So it is based on the use case, first thing.
Mayank: Second thing, if you are having multiple servers, like, okay, you are having 3 servers for… one is for just reading, one is for editing, one is for sending, then it can be 3 clients called as well.
Mayank: So in the backend.
Hardik Vora: Whoa.
Mayank: Main idea is that there is one-to-one connection.
Mayank: So, if your client supports, there can be parallel calls and everything, just like how it happens. So, yeah.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, because in the Gmail, when you were showing, right, how it has been, created, so there was some JSON of edit, then, I mean, the pointers which were showing, right, in the Gmail, how it was happening.
Hardik Vora: So, that is one server where we are connecting directly, as you showed.
Hardik Vora: Gmail directly, you gave the access of all those by checkbox, or by the spinner, and then when you try to send a request as a user to a host.
Hardik Vora: then it, as per the enablement of the request and your user query, it will act as per how much client it is, it requires, I mean, individual relationship of the client. If in a batch it can be done, it will be.
Mayank: Mallab, it will not depend on the server capabilities and everything. Plus, Niko, honestly, Malhab…
Mayank: Via MCP, our main aim is never to optimize things, it is to do it properly.
Hardik Vora: That's true.
Mayank: Sanjee, if you do it one by one as well, it is fine. Normally, you will see it being done one by one, unless you are doing lots of heavy lifting, which never is the case with MCP. MCP is Kalyan.
Mayank: MCPs just need to make the life easy, and when the life gets easy, optimization takes a little backseat.
Hardik Vora: Hmm, okay.
Hardik Vora: Makes sense.
Hardik Vora: And, Mayank, the logs which you showed, right? The log file?
Hardik Vora: So I just asked earlier, I think it got missed by multiple messages, but if the logs are getting generated in local, right, and we have a production Git application, so can't we store this log, or do we specifically need any observability tools?
Mayank: When you will be on production, your application will be running on a server, so long as you'll be on server, not local.
Hardik Vora: correct, okay.
Mayank: The basic Pollo window.
Hardik Vora: Hmm, okay.
Mayank: on the local, because I'm showing you Claude Desktop logs.
Hardik Vora: You were showing in local, so I was thinking in that way.
Mayank: for my… it is me machine. Like, if it be cloud code running on a server, then the logs will also be on a server.
Hardik Vora: Correct, so that lock path, I can give it and I can create a dashboard or something, right?
Mayank: Totally different.
Hardik Vora: understand, or should I… or should I use Langsmeeth or any observator?
Mayank: At what level you want, it's totally simple and on you.
Mayank: Blanksmith might not be directly compatible.
Mayank: See, this is now monitoring the monitoring of Ayropic as you can handle the world.
Hardik Vora: I was thinking on a lead dependency, tool called… that is why I was asking that question.
Mayank: It would be on you how you want to enter the login, and the monitoring part.
Hardik Vora: And one more thing, the accuracy of the user request. I mean, how it will achieve, from a resource. I mean, resource consider… I'm considering resource as a knowledge base for us, as you mentioned.
Mayank: database.
Mayank: Knowledge base is different. It is a resource.
Mayank: It is just some information which is needed. As Sanjee, you will be putting up some
Mayank: 500 pages document and resource. It is just an extra thing. You have to query SQL, then you need a schema. So that schema, we can be kept on that. So it is not a knowledge base. It's a different understanding. It is not the use case like that.
Hardik Vora: So, knowledge bills will be different, and
Mayank: Hmm, only this is driving everything.
Hardik Vora: I mean, resource can be a metadata information, in short.
Mayank: Yeah, exactly, it is a metadata kind of information, yeah.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Hardik Vora: I'm just… Messages, just a second.
Mayank: One minute. Next is Debian, meanwhile.
Mayank: Every one, just a little request. If you have quick doubt, you can ask in the chat.
Hardik Vora: And Mike, just one final thing. The images which you are creating, right? I mean, it's very,
Mayank: It takes a lot of time, kind of mastered it, first did it myself, then…
Mayank: I have multiple skills and other things created, so it's a lumbar process.
Hardik Vora: Because I was trying to understand how you are trying to create.
Mayank: It takes time, although it's not easy. Images, these,
Mayank: Artifacts, all these things which I create.
Hardik Vora: Any tool which we are using for generating the image?
Mayank: There are multiple tools which I use. First, I create them myself, then I try to
Mayank: Take a screenshot, then tell what I want.
Hardik Vora: Oh, I mean multiple processes loading. Okay, okay, got it. Mayank, just one thing, Lakra which we're explaining, 0 to 1 KID, right?
Hardik Vora: So, there you mentioned, after the one… I mean, it will get incremented, but I think,
Hardik Vora: in the whole logs, when you're scrolling, that ID was still the same, ID equal to 1.
Mayank: Nayanito. I told you that when I was explaining. He… it is shutting down every time.
Hardik Vora: Oh, it is shutting down, that is why it is resetting. Okay.
Mayank: When it starts again, it will be again starting with that idea thing. So yeah, people, yeah.
Mayank: Yo.
Hardik Vora: And any reason it was automatically shutting down, or you had intentionally…
Mayank: It is not automatic, I did that shit, though.
Hardik Vora: Oh, okay, okay, okay.
Mayank: I did not use this ever Macharla bit, just the initialization happened.
Mayank: I did not use data much, though. Apple Notes, I think I just used one or twice.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Hardik Vora: And, mind that versioning negotiation and what the next part we're showing now.
Mayank: the ability negotiation.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, yeah. You can just start from tomorrow so that it will be fresh.
Mayank: opportunity negotiation has to start, versioning has done.
Mayank: Revise it. The notes are very, very.
Hardik Vora: So, Mike, just one thing.
Mayank: Hardikodas are clear, we are quick, we will.
Hardik Vora: No, no, I got it, I got it, Mike, I understood. I'm just, trying to understand, k server work, I mean, the MCP server, which we already have, right? Gmail, Slack, and all. How will we understand what, version they are handling? I mean, what version?
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Mayank: Now you know, Nikita me and say, GJ, like, if it is not working.
Hardik Vora: The exclamation what you were showing for NHN.
Mayank: We will have to now check, na?
Mayank: will be updated frequently. When you are working in a company and you are creating these servers or clients.
Hardik Vora: Correct.
Mayank: That is where you will get that error. So now you know, k sahi, this is the problem.
Hardik Vora: Mhmh.
Mayank: So, that is the case. In the backend, everything is happening right.
Hardik Vora: Got it. Thanks, thanks, man, and take care.
Mayank: Thank you.
Mayank: Debian?
Debayan: Yes, am I audible?
Mayank: Yes.
Debayan: Okay, okay, my question is related to that versioning, that when the client needs to initialize, with the MCP server to, this
Debayan: Does it send all the versions that it needs to, need, for that application, or it just sends the, recent one, for the latest one?
Mayank: It send all the version, let me quickly check the 1-1 minute, just give me a minute. Actually, I was also a little bit confused, let me check and see what it…
Mayank: I couldn't… Introduction, Logan.
Mayank: Cheers.
Mayank: So, this is how it happens. Client send…
Mayank: One minute, wait a minute.
Mayank: Thank you.
Mayank: Okay, so the way it happened is that client sends the version widget supports the latest and everything, all the versions.
Mayank: And then the server, okay.
Debayan: That's…
Mayank: it makes sure that if it supports any of the version… let me, let me actually, show you the def… well, you can read it and you will get the item. The Thora site is technical, but this is what it is, the documentation Mehra.
Mayank: So, this is exactly how it happens. In the initialization request, the client must send a protocol version it supports, yeah?
Mayank: This should be the latest version supported by the client. The client should make sure Kit is sending the protocol version it supports.
Mayank: And… It is…
Mayank: the latest version, not like you are saying, hey, I support Windows 7 as well, no, Windows 11, 10, 7 as well. If the supporters… if the server supports the requested version, it must respond with the same version.
Mayank: Otherwise, the server must respond with another protocol version it supports.
Mayank: This should be the latest version supported by the server. So, how can I explain you that? Let's say…
Mayank: Key, just a very basic example.
Mayank: There is Windows, and there is an application, or a game, GTA 5.
Mayank: Not sure how many of you are aware about DirectX. So, Windows says ki… Windows 11 says kibi, I can support DirectX.
Mayank: Then… And maybe DirectX 11.
Mayank: Now, if your server supports 10, it should respond and say that, hey, AI supports 10. If it supports 11, 11, it should send the latest one. It should not be kini, I support both of them, so I will just say, no, no, it should send the latest one.
Mayank: Now, if it doesn't.
Mayank: Then it should send the latest one it supports, so it can maybe respond with direct text.
Mayank: 8, maybe, because it supports 6, 7, 8, so it will send with 8.
Mayank: So otherwise, the server must respond with another protocol virginate Support. This should be the latest version.
Mayank: Okay? If the client does not support the version in the server, it should disconnect. So that is how it happens.
Debayan: Oh, goodness.
Mayank: both of them tell, Deepak these are all the versions I support, latest, so that any connection which happened, that happens on the latest. As an example.
Mayank: A very basic example. If you and me, we want to run something.
Mayank: If it can be run on Windows XP and 7 and 8, we will be running it on 8, not on XP.
Mayank: Deca?
Debayan: Okay.
Mayank: So that is how it happened. The documentation here, I can share the link, you can read through it. I highly suggest to always read the documentation. It may not only be my Sidd.
Mayank: Our screen is shared, Hardik.
Mayank: You're able to see the screen, right? Debra?
Debayan: Yes, Anthony.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: So, Malhtar load, this is the best one. Actually, it has been also changed a little bit, but Abhi is being followed, so it should be fine.
Mayank: Although it will be getting followed for at least 2 years more, I know.
Debayan: Okay, I was okay.
Mayank: Minute.
Mayank: Gopal Krishna.
Gopikrishnan N: Yeah, Mayanka, yeah.
Mayank: Yeah. Oh, yes.
Gopikrishnan N: No problem. So Mayanka, like, you already explained, like, so that the two-way communication that is happening, between the… so for the SNRPC. So, I didn't get fully, understood, like, so, like, usually for that normal API send out, we will just
Gopikrishnan N: hitting that request. Means, we'll be calling that AP, and we'll be getting the response. But, so, what exactly the need for the MCP to call the client.
Mayank: privilege.
Gopikrishnan N: Any good…
Mayank: I get the question. You are… you are asking about the two-way communication with JSON IPC support, right? See?
Gopikrishnan N: Kick, get it.
Mayank: Normally what happens in any HTTP API server, if you were to have ever worked, which for sure you would have worked.
Mayank: Client can only make a call to the server.
Gopikrishnan N: Yeah.
Mayank: Right? Client can only make the call to the server.
Gopikrishnan N: Cut it.
Mayank: Okay? It's not the other way around. Well, look, when the client asks for a call, it gets
Mayank: the response.
Mayank: Make sense?
Gopikrishnan N: Yes, yeah.
Mayank: In JSON RPC, server can also make the call.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: Server can initiate a call.
Mayank: That is the difference. That is what is meant by two-way communication. HTTP APIs are one-way communication, only client can call the server. Server respond back to the request of the client.
Mayank: It is… it is able to connect, like, server is sending the information, but server never initiates a request.
Mayank: In two-way communication in any system, and what JSON RPC is about, irrespective of MCP, I'm telling you, server can also call the client, and it happens, like, in this server, do mention that, hey, this is… like, I will show you, like, it was there, and…
Mayank: which feature it was. It was there, I will show you, like, I'm not able to get it, right now, but yeah, this is how it happens.
Mayank: Beautiful.
Gopikrishnan N: Okay, and what is the reason why the server is calling that client?
Mayank: So, when there are long-running tasks in MCP architecture, when, let's say, it will take time, plus when there is a way, like, let's say, as an example.
Mayank: you are asking me to, do something via… on my MCP server, so I can tell you that how much of it has been completed, how much time it paid, so all those communications server can tell. So rather than client polling me and everything, it is able to do that.
Gopikrishnan N: related to the synchronous communication. Once it is completed, it is coming back to the responding… Yeah, synchronous is different.
Mayank: process when you make a call, and it is working in the backend, and you will get the response once it is done.
Mayank: But you can continue with other work. Here, it can send multiple requests as well.
Mayank: So, asynchronous and that, read about it, it's a little different. Asynchronous calls are when you are making… when you make a call, you are like, okay, I will catch the response afterward, let me continue with my work.
Mayank: So, it is still open and everything. In here.
Mayank: Again, asynchronous as well, you make the initial call.
Gopikrishnan N: Teja? Yeah.
Mayank: Your asynchronous server is not calling you ever.
Mayank: So it is also asynchronous with HTTP server. It is not two ways, it is always one way.
Gopikrishnan N: Okay, okay.
Mayank: Nadeem never your asynchronous server calls, you know? You always close your server asynchronously.
Mayank: I hope that makes sense.
Gopikrishnan N: Got it, got it.
Mayank: So that is the case.
Gopikrishnan N: Okay, yeah, thank you.
Mayank: Just read about it a little bit.
Gopikrishnan N: Yeah, some of the interviews.
Mayank: But yeah, it's a good thing to read. I enjoy these, because these are all better than what make your system design strong.
Gopikrishnan N: Okay, yeah, thanks, thanks, boy. Take care.
Mayank: Jitendra, and you all will not believe, although just yesterday, I was having a call with the co-founder and CEO of her team.
Mayank: And he was saying… so I needed a… I needed an API for some checking of the data. He said that I will send you a CSV file every 5 minutes, but right now we are not developing APIs, so I'm not sure why KSTO MLFT guy, company might be also doing good, but I thought that API would have been better, but should be fine.
Mayank: So you… we should be up to about these things.
Mayank: Jitendra?
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, hi, Mike. My question is MCP, like, see, MCP, you have, you mentioned that you have a, like, primary, like, primitive
Jitendra Biswal: Features, manage your.
Mayank: Limitives are just, deliverables or…
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah, like a tool, like a tool, resource, and prompt.
Mayank: Google's imports, yeah.
Jitendra Biswal: thumb.
Jitendra Biswal: So, I was just comparing with the GitHub, MCP, and I just checked in the,
Jitendra Biswal: So, in a GitHub published in CP, they don't have any, resource and RAMP.
Mayank: Oh. It goes.
Jitendra Biswal: they are not, I mean, you don't know what will be your resource, right?
Jitendra Biswal: Absolutely.
Mayank: It is totally fine. It is not a requirement key you have to create a…
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah, that's right, because whatever the.
Mayank: 95% of the cases.
Jitendra Biswal: Hello?
Mayank: Hello?
Jitendra Biswal: I mean, I didn't.
Mayank: Yes, it's your birthday.
Jitendra Biswal: I think your voice gets slow.
Mayank: One minute. Although I'm speaking slow, but is it better now?
Jitendra Biswal: Oh, okay, yes.
Mayank: So…
Jitendra Biswal: Can I derive this, my MCP? I create my custom MCP from the GitHub provided MCP, or I need to write my own, MCP from the ground up?
Mayank: I think I told you… told someone this, so you can…
Mayank: Have your MCP call another MCP.
Mayank: So I think in that ways, it is… Kind of possible.
Mayank: But… I don't think the…
Mayank: This inheritance work directly key you are having, but…
Mayank: Otherwise, as well, I don't think it will be very difficult. So, your MCP, as it can call other MCPs, you can easily have it call for tools and for other things, you can create your own.
Jitendra Biswal: No, no, I don't have to write anything again for this, whatever they inherently come from, like, a list.
Jitendra Biswal: all the tools that GitHub,
Mayank: So that is what I'm saying. You can call GitHub MCP
Mayank: from your MCP. Your MCP can call other MCP.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, I have to call that entity.
Mayank: Because it's an MCP server only, like, it does not care a… you have these files and everything.
Mayank: That's a simple MCP server, which you can start, and your MCP can call other MCPs.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, okay. And, second thing is, like, I saw that we are writing from the past MCP, J, base.
Jitendra Biswal: So, is it the only one, or… I mean, right?
Mayank: multiple, I think, FastMCP is state-of-the-art, there is Anthropic, official one as well.
Jitendra Biswal: YC.
Mayank: So, like, it's just that FastMCP is the most used one, the best one, so…
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, so that means all the companies, they release their SDK, right?
Mayank: No, no, no, no.
Mayank: You are asking for creating MCP servers, right?
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah, yeah, the getting MCP, I saw that we are using a fast MCP, right?
Mayank: consolete.
Jitendra Biswal: the pose.
Mayank: for creating MCPs, there will be multiple SDKs.
Mayank: The most famous one are the official one, which is your MCP from Anthropic.
Mayank: The MCPSDK.
Mayank: and FastMCP. Every company will have their own MCP server. They will not have the way of getting MCP. They will be using any one of them.
Jitendra Biswal: So, what is the difference, then, between them? I mean…
Mayank: It's no difference how you can create…
Jitendra Biswal: Can we create another hour SDK?
Mayank: Oh, you can… please stop me.
Mayank: No, he was also hit hit by someone else.
Jitendra Biswal: So, what is the base… that best libraries that is required?
Mayank: There is never an answer of what is best to take.
Jitendra Biswal: No, no, base library, not base. Base, base library.
Mayank: Yes, Naiduid.
Jitendra Biswal: Ian.
Mayank: It will be all these concepts only, you know, we will be understanding. So, base library might be this Python SDK, which SDK people have provided, MCP people have provided.
Mayank: the base. I hope you… do you know about Keras and TensorFlow, by any chance?
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah, yeah.
Mayank: TensorFlow and Keras, same thing.
Mayank: This, you can understand about TensorFlow, fast MCPS.
Jitendra Biswal: Oh, I see. Okay.
Mayank: that. Exact same thing.
Mayank: So, for Chiras, the base is TensorFlow only, but it made it very easy, right?
Mayank: Rather, it made it that easy, he… Google put in… Karas inside it only.
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah, I know.
Mayank: the base. Now, the base for the whatever this is being created by the main people, that would be the base. Now it's on you how you want to make it easy. So, make it easy, as much as you want.
Mayank: Huh.
Mayank: Any other topic?
Mayank: Sandeep?
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah.
Jitendra Biswal: Good, thank you.
Mayank: Jitendra, sorry, I think your voice got put.
Sandeep Kumar: B.
Mayank: was all right.
Jitendra Biswal: Hi. No, no, I'm fine, I'm fine.
Jitendra Biswal: Got it.
Mayank: I sent you.
Sandeep Kumar: Mmm.
Sandeep Kumar: Hi, Meng, good day.
Mayank: Okay.
Sandeep Kumar: Am I, am I audible?
Mayank: Huh, you're audible, you're audible.
Sandeep Kumar: Yeah, I have only one question that, we have received watches from our company to write a cloud certification.
Sandeep Kumar: Of the foundation one.
Sandeep Kumar: So, however, I'm going through the cloud documents and videos, so any suggestion from your end to just…
Mayank: Desmuth, if you can. I am already working on the content. Rather, I have connected with two people from your batch who have cleared this out.
Mayank: Okay. I will combine all of them and create a video and upload it, so that all of you can go through it, and I feel that it will be much helpful.
Sandeep Kumar: Okay, that would be great. Thank you, thanks.
Mayank: Okay, because I'm already researching, they have expanded this immediately, there was one exam, now they've made it four exams.
Sandeep Kumar: Yes, yes, that's correct.
Sandeep Kumar: Thank you.
Mayank: Okay?
Mayank: But just keep underminding me so that I don't miss out.
Mayank: Boswinda.
Mayank: And Rajeev, you are the last one.
Mayank: Biswal now.
Mayank: Rajeev?
Mayank: Swanar Rajiv.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, man.
Mayank: Yes, yes, you're audible long.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, you don't need to answer for this.
Mayank: You should be fine, I can answer.
Basavanna Olekar: Just try to have warm water.
Basavanna Olekar: A little bit of salt, gargle 3 times, it will help a lot.
Mayank: I'm doing it, so I'm… for the last C, what happened was that Tuesday, I kind of got a sore throat, okay?
Mayank: So, I took…
Mayank: I have been drinking 4 or 5 hot things, doing gargals with that. Betaden is there, when beta-den for gargal is there.
Mayank: Weirdly enough, two days back, it got bad. Although on Thursday night, it got very bad.
Mayank: So, thanks for your, suggestion. I will take it. I will actually go in Gargal just right now, because I have a class at the night as well, and I have…
Mayank: two calls, like, one client call and one has another call, so photos are backed up there. But, the way, I will surely take… surely do that.
Basavanna Olekar: No need to talk, like, you know, I stay in US. I stay here from so many parts of the country, like, the world, many country people, that's the one golden remedy.
Mayank: That goes, yeah, with water, yeah.
Basavanna Olekar: called Garggle 3.
Basavanna Olekar: All your throat infection and issues.
Mayank: Oh, Nini, that is the case.
Basavanna Olekar: But unfortunately, you are in the business where you need to talk, so just try to reduce.
Mayank: I am trying, actually, and, I'm just actually trying, but somehow it got bad on Thursday, so people won't believe I am taking so many hot things for my throat, the kaly mechi, which is black pepper.
Mayank: But yeah, let's, let's hope. It will come around in a 3-4 days.
Basavanna Olekar: Avoid as much as possible to talk.
Mayank: Yeah.
Basavanna Olekar: I'll harass you next… in the next hour or the other next class, don't worry.
Mayank: Sure, no, it's very, very happy, so should be fine. Like, I'm still happy to clear the routes, yes.
Basavanna Olekar: No, no, no, no, no, no.
Mayank: We… And everything is pretty bad, so yeah.
Mayank: Yeah,
Basavanna Olekar: Thanks so much.
Mayank: But thanks a lot for your concern. I really appreciate it.
Mayank: Rajeev, you can ask your doubt.
Mayank: Hi, Chief.
Mayank: Rajeevs.
Rajeev: Can you hear me?
Mayank: Yes, now you're unable.
Rajeev: So, this MCP is streamable, right? So, it's, like, correct?
Mayank: HTTPS…
Rajeev: A stream available, right? So it's, it's like, it's, it's common stream, right? So, a stream MB will…
Rajeev: something, there is a terminology, they use technical terminology, keyword, right? So, MCP is estimable, so we can stream that.
Rajeev: Data, correct?
Mayank: Sorry, can you repeat it?
Rajeev: No, no, see, there is two things, right? So, you were discussing the test. There is a MCP, and there is a… which works on this JSON RPC, right?
Rajeev: And we have a vaib socket connection also, right? Which also works on the JSN RPC, right?
Mayank: Mhmh.
Rajeev: Good thing.
Rajeev: So, what I was asking, you know, so… but as we know that, right? So, this WebSocket work on the live connection, it's always okay.
Rajeev: And it's, it's like, it's both ways, right?
Mayank: Yes, it is also both ways, yeah.
Rajeev: Both ways. But I think MCP, it's unidirectional, right? Or it's both.
Mayank: Really, it is, it is both ways, it is. See, what do you mean by both ways? When either of.
Rajeev: Okay, both… I mean, see, I can also see, it's from the… see, we send a request, right, to the server.
Rajeev: And Saravan, you know, you know, send me the data.
Mayank: No, no, no.
Rajeev: That is the response, the client, like, from the client, we send the server server…
Mayank: It's not both ways.
Rajeev: Yeah, it's not a worthy, right?
Rajeev: Why we are saying this to me, well, like, you know, so…
Mayank: I'm explaining you, when you send a request to the server and server replies back.
Mayank: That is not both ways, that's a unidirectional.
Mayank: It is said both ways when both server and client can make a request.
Mayank: Right, right, right. Example.
Mayank: In MCP, I will show you
Mayank: Practically, I will have to see how to, replicate that, but server can also send the request to the client.
Mayank: I'm just saying HTTP, normal post, HTTPS?
Mayank: one way. It is not two ways. But there as well, when a client asks for something, server sends it back, right?
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: So, but still it is one way, because… Hit?
Mayank: Server can never make a call to the client.
Rajeev: What's a hard time?
Mayank: I hope it is clear. So, both cases when you can call me, and I can call you as well. If only I can call you, of course you will reply back to me with that response you will give me, but it is still unidirectional.
Rajeev: Okay. So what is, like, you know, we already have, you know, this one, HTTP, right? Those REST API.
Rajeev: And what, like, you know, what is the difference between this MCP and those just API HTTP?
Mayank: Meaning, because MCP is a different concept.
Rajeev: Mhmh.
Mayank: Whenever there's a communication, there are protocols and everything which is selected. For example, MCP is going with JSON RPC, and JSON RPC supports two ways.
Mayank: Okay.
Rajeev: Okay.
Rajeev: Top.
Mayank: Peddirectional Panda.
Rajeev: But here it is unidirectional only, right?
Mayank: Nikita is two directions. In MCP, you were asking, right?
Rajeev: Yeah, yeah, MCP.
Mayank: it is two-directional, not by unidirectional. It uses that… it uses that thing where it sends… the server sends back to the client the request and everything.
Rajeev: Okay.
Mayank: It is bidirectional only.
Rajeev: It's wider, okay.
Mayank: Yeah.
Rajeev: Should be gone.
Mayank: So CP, it is also bidirectional, yeah.
Rajeev: Okay, okay.
Rajeev: And, alright.
Rajeev: And all… we are discussing this, right? Creating this tool, right? So all this tool, right?
Rajeev: So, whatever we are discussing, like Gmail server and all, maybe some Confluence, some Jira server, right? So, those are, like, their server, right? But if I want to create my own server, MCP server, for example.
Rajeev: I have my project, right? So my… I'm basically… we are using an application, ABC application. So where the, you know, users are coming, and they are…
Rajeev: there are some certain UI, they are filling up this jail, and they're getting… they're downloading some grade, all this data.
Rajeev: But it's the same thing, right? So, when, you know, when we are creating the chat board or something, Agentic, right? So, there we have to create those MCP servers, right?
Rajeev: To connect to my database.
Mayank: Mhmh.
Rajeev: That's where this MCP will come in the picture, right?
Mayank: We will be creating our own servers.
Mayank: In future, for any application which we create.
Rajeev: Greg, for example.
Mayank: Would you have mute.
Rajeev: some Oracle, right? There are some Oracle databases, so…
Mayank: Oh.
Rajeev: the SUM REST API.
Mayank: Yep.
Rajeev: So those things, you know, so we can use… consume those through MCP and give those to the… to those, you know.
Mayank: To the AI application.
Rajeev: for the LLM.
Mayank: Yeah.
Rajeev: Okay, so that's where this MCP will come, right, so…
Mayank: The usage is to… you see cloud and connectors, right?
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: That is all MCP usage.
Rajeev: Yeah, yeah, correct, that is one of the uses, but…
Rajeev: We can also use in those Asant, right? So that's where, like, you know, we can give those LLM
Rajeev: MCP.
Mayank: Matrav, see, to give access to an AI application, which… Mhab, I explained in the last two last tasks properly in depth, but just to summarize.
Mayank: If you have to give AI application access to your access to your tools and your thing, it is the best way of doing it. Simple as that.
Rajeev: But one thing, actually, still I'm not understanding. So, they are saying that MC, LLM is having some brain, right? And they're using the brain to connect this MCP.
Rajeev: Because we are providing those, you know, those context engineering, right, those more details.
Mayank: Mhmh.
Rajeev: That's where this, you know, MCP is coming in the picture. It's, you know, that… but why can't… can we use the same thing in the HTTP also? Suppose I don't want to predict extra MCP. I simply… I have some server.
Mayank: Actually, there is a problem which I discussed, Key. For example, if you have, like, if you're getting it with HTTP, right?
Rajeev: Huh.
Mayank: So, then you will have to maintain it, create it at multiple places.
Mayank: So it is not scalable that much. There are some problems in that, which I discussed. It can be done, not a problem.
Mayank: But is it the best way out? A little debatable.
Mayank: Is it something which… is easiest, yes, for sure, because that is the reason everyone is going towards MCP.
Mayank: So, performance, maybe we can debate on this optimizing the performance, but ease of… ease of usability and everything, MCB is pretty good in that.
Rajeev: Okay. Yeah, correct, that is true.
Mayank: companies dating their MCPs, that only.
Rajeev: Right, right, so…
Rajeev: Actually, we have the same, actually, we are also doing the same, you know, we are creating some… some… some in those, you know, this chatbot, right? Agentic AI.
Rajeev: Boat, vote.
Rajeev: So, we asked the same question, right? They're also, like, you know, we already have the server, right? We already have the Suresh API created.
Mayank: Have you attended the last two last week class? Last week, there was no class. 22nd sep…
Rajeev: Yeah, I was there. I was there, I asked the same question there at that time also.
Mayank: I will quickly explain you. See, when you are having an API server.
Rajeev: Okay. Huh.
Mayank: You will be creating separate tools for each of these APIs?
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: Nope.
Mayank: If there are…
Mayank: 100 people in your organization, or 100 teams, all of them will be creating their own pools?
Rajeev: R-right.
Mayank: If you want to connect to an API, you will have to define. That was supported in HRGPT.
Rajeev: Bye.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: Now, let's just as a very basic example. If tomorrow you change your API, you launched a V2, or you changed some parameters in that.
Mayank: You would have to do the change at all these things? All the hundred things?
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: So that's the problem a little bit.
Mayank: Plus, one more thing.
Mayank: you will have to specifically tell that, hey, this is where you have to hit. Plus, normally, for example, in Gmail, there are 15 actions. So you will have to create tools for those 15 actions.
Rajeev: Right, correct.
Mayank: Now, think about this key. Scalability level pay. I showed you this very nice, thing as well, I… not sure if you remember it.
Mayank: One minute, I will show you again.
Rajeev: No, basically, what I'm trying to understand, right, like, you know, we have payload here also, AMCP also, we have payload interest AP also.
Mayank: Huh.
Rajeev: But they are saying we can reuse, you know, some of that, you know, we don't have to write again and again.
Mayank: You can use your SS. In the ideally sense, like, MCP is just using API in the backend, but it has been very nicely, abstracted.
Rajeev: Hmm.
Mayank: That's a better way of seeing it. Like, when you're sending email using MCP,
Mayank: And even when MCP is getting used. But now, think about, as a layman user.
Mayank: You don't have to go in depth of it, right? He can just ask the AI, and AI will do it for it. Because AI knows with this protocol.
Mayank: Doing it directly via HTTP protocol is not that simple.
Rajeev: Okay.
Mayank: So, a little bit around that, plus, as I mentioned, the tool which I showed you, like, the thing which I showed you.
Mayank: Huh.
Mayank: The Akashi, Let's say if you are having… 5 apps, Claude, VS Code.
Mayank: Cha GPT, and if you, let's say, if they need 5 tools. So this is 25 separate integrations you will have to write, test, and keep working every time.
Mayank: Right?
Mayank: With MCP, that reduces a lot more, but we'll just reduce to this much 5.
Mayank: Rather, it just depends on the number of tools.
Mayank: Because MCP protocol kind of handles that in a better way.
Mayank: you are owning, or the owner of MCP Server is owning everything, so instead of NN2M, it is N plus M.
Mayank: Just that. So that is the benefit.
Rajeev: Okay.
Mayank: I hope you… if you have ever worked with servers and everything, you will know that, hey, how difficult is it to maintain the refers and all these things?
Mayank: So that is where the problem will happen.
Rajeev: Okay.
Rajeev: Yeah. And how, like, you know, one way is, like, in this cloud desktop, right, so connect to those MCP. Is there any other way, like, also, suppose if I'm creating MCP on local, right, I want to test those MCP.
Mayank: And multiple ways, just like Client Survive. Postman supports it. You can hit the call directly as well. Multiple ways are there. Just, you should be having a client. Client can connect to the server.
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: MCP client we can create via code.
Mayank: So, just like how I've shown you, just having to show you an example here as well, see?
Mayank: MCP client past MCP. Just create that directly via code.
Mayank: And see, so server is there, client is there as well.
Mayank: client. You just give it where you want to connect it.
Mayank: And, Mahabini local script as well. Just keep on working on it. Similarly, Postman now supports Postman MCP.
Mayank: See?
Mayank: Postman now supports you can have an MCP directory. It should be client, just like how we have C. It's very simple. How we hit an API which is posted. We need a client to hit it, right? It can be a curl request, it can be postman, it can be an application.
Mayank: Same base, nothing else.
Rajeev: Okay.
Mayank: Pallab, I think what I will suggest is, Pallab, I also have a very hard time on finding my brain around it. It is…
Mayank: a lot… Abstracted API calls only.
Mayank: but… which is optimized for AI. Muralav, if you will think, Navalav, as a design expert, even I will… I also find MCP a little bit useless, to be honest. But then, I also got around it, and I understand what is the use case. If you zoom out and understand it for the normal public.
Mayank: So that phase, it is a little different thing.
Rajeev: Correct. So basically, yeah, this would be… they made a.
Mayank: The second you…
Rajeev: Chandra.
Mayank: The second you ask a normal person that, hey, there are 15 APIs.
Mayank: for Gmail, connect to one you want, he will not use that. So MCP helps that there.
Rajeev: So basically, as you already told, right, like, so basically, you know, here, LLM is in everything, right? So…
Rajeev: So, we are basically giving all those contexts.
Mayank: Oh, well, that'd be it to be vaibhav.
Rajeev: It's taking that position.
Mayank: I just have to use it, yeah.
Mayank: And the main point is key, the reason it went back to the Gmail guys or GitHub guys is because
Mayank: If they don't take it up, their application might not get easily integrated. By the way, Gmail doesn't provide the MCP server, so people will tell that people will not use Gmail in 2-3 years, because it is not by AI. Thoda State is just making things easy, nothing else.
Rajeev: Very quick.
Mayank: Core is the same. Core is exactly the same. It is still API, it is still server, it is still scale up, scale down, everything will be the same.
Rajeev: Right, right.
Rajeev: Yeah.
Rajeev: That's all. That's all mine. Thank you.
Mayank: Cool. So, yeah, I think that was all the doubts, everyone. Thanks a lot, please revise, and let's meet tomorrow. Really out of…
Mayank: energy, so anyways…
Mayank: Hello, I hope you had a good time, and yeah, we will be covering things in depth, so you are actually interview-ready when you say. And I will share the resources by
Mayank: evening… okay, I have to rush somewhere, about 11.30, Janata, but it should be fine. So, around 4… 3 or 4, I will sit back on my machine, and then I will upload your resources.
Mayank: If anyone has anything which I left out, please send me the… Email.
Mayank: And please send me the CVs if you're in the right experience band. I want that you do get the jobs, okay?
Mayank: Thank you.